we've got about 6 years before
距离
everything changes and we thought money
一切都改变还有大约六年时间，我们曾经
in the bank was safe we thought our
以为银行里的钱很安全，
house was safe but none of that true and
房子也很安全，但事实并非如此。
the moment you put your money and your
一旦你把钱和
savings in the bank you don't own
积蓄存入银行，你就什么都不拥有了，
anything and your future self is getting
未来的你
poorer by 11% every year and that's the
每年都会缩水11%。这就是
problem for Financial Security and
财务安全和
wealth creation but I know where the
财富积累的问题所在。但我知道
opportunities lie and I thought answers
机会在哪里，也找到了答案。
so could you explain it to me through
你能结合
the context of this okay so Raul pal is
以下情况解释一下吗？好的，Raul Pal是
the Ever Changing world of modern
瞬息万变的现代
Finance unpacking the secet of crypto
金融界最具影响力的人物之一，他揭示了加密货币的秘密
and how to build wealth in an uncertain
以及如何在不确定的未来积累财富。
future people know their Futures they
人们了解自己的未来，他们
can't afford to buy house they have less
买不起房，
savings debts from University people in
积蓄减少，背负着大学债务，这些人已经
their 30s the first generation that
30多岁了，是第一代
won't be as rich as their parents so
无法像父母那样富有的人。那么，
what advice would you give to set myself
你会给我什么建议来为
up for wealth in the future you start
未来的财富积累做好准备呢？开始
investing but what about the people that
投资。但是对于那些
no matter how hard they work they still
无论多么努力工作仍然
don't have that excess income to invest
没有额外收入进行投资的人来说该怎么办呢？
you don't need huge savings you just
你不需要巨额积蓄，你只
need to understand how to look for
需要知道如何寻找
opportunities for example the S&amp;P 500 is
机会，例如标普500指数。  500美元
not worth your time real estate doesn't
不值得你浪费时间，房地产
really make you any money those days are
根本赚不了钱，那种日子已经
gone gold actually lost you money but
一去不复返了。黄金实际上会让你赔钱，但
investing in crypto like Bitcoin gives
投资像比特币这样的加密货币却能
us stupidly High returns in shorter
在短时间内带来极高的回报，
periods of time growing at 150% a year
年增长率高达150%，
scaling at twice the speed of the
扩展速度是互联网的两倍。
internet so now the guy with $500 can
所以现在，即使只有500美元，也能
get rich a couple of questions here then
致富。接下来我问几个问题。
so I'm now 30 years oldish have I missed
我现在30岁左右，是不是错过了最佳
the boat no much of the reason why I
时机？不，我
think people don't invest in crypto is
觉得人们不投资加密货币的原因是，
they've heard stories where people have
他们听说过一些人
put too much in and they've lost it all
投入太多资金后血本无归的故事。万一
what if you're wrong we're going to talk
你错了呢？接下来我们会讨论
about how lot to it up and then how do I
如何筹集资金，以及如何
invest in crypto it's really simple
投资加密货币。其实很简单，万事开头难，只要迈出第一步，
do that and you'll make
你就能
money this has always blown my mind a
赚钱。这一点一直让我有点惊讶：
show regularly haven't yet subscribed to
经常收听我们节目的听众中，有53%还没有订阅我们的
the show so could I ask you for a favor
节目。所以，在我们开始之前，能否请你帮个忙？
before we start if you like the show and
如果你喜欢我们的节目，
you like what we do here and you want to
喜欢我们所做的一切，并且想
support us the free simple way that you
支持我们，你可以用最简单的免费方式订阅。 只需
can do just that is by hitting the
点击
Subscribe button and my commitment to
订阅按钮即可。我向
you is if you do that then I'll do
您承诺，如果您订阅，
everything in my power me and my team to
我和我的团队将竭尽全力
make sure that this show is better for
确保
you every single week we'll listen to
每周节目都能为您带来更好的体验。我们会认真听取
your feedback we'll find the guest that
您的反馈，找到您
you want me to speak to and we'll
想让我采访的嘉宾，并
continue to do what we do thank you so
继续做好我们一直在做的事情。非常感谢！
much well from a very high level
从宏观的
perspective and I'm being unspecific
角度来看，我在
here so I'm looking for an unspecific
这里没有具体说明，所以我想听一个比较笼统的
answer what exactly is the mission that
答案：
you're on in this season of your life
您在这个人生阶段的使命是什么？
like who what are you doing and who are
您在做什么？您为谁而做？
for so obviously you do it for yourself
显然，您是为了自己而做。
but really I think that I've been armed
但实际上，我认为我在过去
my 30-year career that I kind of have a
30年的职业生涯中积累了丰富的工具和知识，让我对
decent sense of where the world is going
世界的发展方向、
where the opportunities lie and where
机遇和
the risk lies for people and I can see
风险有了相当清晰的认识。我能看到
the problems people are facing and I
人们面临的问题，而且我
think I've got answers so what I want to
认为我能找到答案。所以我想做的就是
do is help as many people as possible in
在这段旅程中尽可能多地帮助人们。之所以会这样，是因为
was I was in Spain back in
我在
2012 and also during the fin finial
2012年身处西班牙，以及在……期间。
2008 and I was writing macroeconomic
2008年金融危机爆发时，我正在为
research for my research service Global
我的研究服务机构“全球
macro investor and I had seen it coming
宏观投资者”撰写宏观经济研究报告。我早就预料到了这场危机，
I predicted it I knew it was coming I
我预测到了它，我知道它即将到来，我
knew the problems I warned all of my
知道会遇到哪些问题。我警告过所有的
friends that nobody listened we
朋友，但没人听我的。
that was that when we got to the
我们都明白金融危机的严重性，也知道将会发生什么。因为我住在西班牙的一个海滨小镇，他们大多从事房地产，结果全都破产了。更糟糕的是，当
European crisis when basically the
危机蔓延到欧洲时，
governments of Europe ran out of money
欧洲各国政府资金短缺，
the banks also ran out of money and as
银行也随之破产。
opposed to being bailed out they got
他们没有得到政府的救助，而是采取了
what known as bailed in which means that
所谓的“内部救助”，这意味着政府
they took your
动用了你的
savings to pay the
存款来偿还
total faith in the system so Occupy Wall
债务。我父母的朋友和朋友的朋友都损失惨重，他们质问：为什么我们事先不知道？这个问题一直萦绕在我心头：为什么我们事先不知道？我发现每个人都对整个体系彻底失去了信心。就在
Street happened at the same period and
同一时期，“占领华尔街”运动爆发了，
it was people angry it's like we thought
人们愤怒不已。我们曾经以为
money in the bank was safe we thought
银行里的钱是安全的，
our house was safe we thought the system
房子是安全的，整个体系会保护
was there for us and suddenly they all
我们。 突然间，他们都
wake up and realize the system was not
醒悟过来，意识到这个体系并非
there for them it was actually for other
为他们而设，而是为其他
people you know people talk about
人准备的。你知道，人们常说
Bankers never went to jail no there was
银行家从不坐牢，确实如此。总有一种
there was that sense that it it was
感觉，这件事从未真正
concluded and it sat with me for a long
结束。这种感觉萦绕在我心头很久，我一直在
time thinking what can I do about this
思考我能做些什么。
because I was writing super high-end
因为我当时为
kind of research for hedge funds and you
对冲基金和
know big Asset Management firms and so
大型资产管理公司撰写高端研究报告，所以
it wasn't accessible to people um and
普通人根本接触不到。
then I wrote a couple of Articles one
后来我写了几篇文章，其中一篇
got leaked in Zero Hedge in its early
在Zero Hedge早期就被泄露了，
days and it became super viral um and I
并迅速传播开来。我
thought maybe there's something here
想，或许
that I could reach a broader audience
我可以触及更广泛的受众，这样就能
because then I can help these people
帮助这些人。于是，
and that's when we came up with the idea
我们萌生了“
of real Vision which was the idea of
Real Vision”的想法，即
interviewing the people at the very
采访
heart of the system and kind of sharing
体系核心人物，分享他们的经历和
the details because these people weren't
细节。因为这些人并没有
hiding it they wanted to help people as
隐瞒，他们也想帮助别人。
well everyone had that sense that we
每个人都觉得我们
could help people so I'm still on that
能够帮助别人。所以我仍在探索这条
journey and that Journey kind of has
道路，这条路
taken a multitude of paths starting
走了很多弯路，包括
businesses but also just trying to
创业，也包括努力让
educate people on why they feel the way
人们理解他们为什么会有这样的感受，
they do you know why politics is so
比如政治。 现在
polarized never used to be this bad you
两极分化太严重了，以前从来没这么糟糕过。你
know what's really going on and who
知道到底发生了什么，该
blame and what to do about it if I stop
怪谁，以及该怎么做吗？如果我
the average person on the street that
在街上随便拦住一个
knows you and watch is real vision and I
认识你的普通人，
ask them what has R and His Channel and
问问他R和他的频道以及
his information done for you what do you
他提供的信息对你有什么帮助，你
think they would say the average person
觉得他们会怎么说？普通人
they just say thank you because we've
只会说谢谢，因为我们
helped
帮助他们
demystify it the world of finance and
揭开了金融世界的神秘面纱。
you see we all have
你看，我们每个人都有
the root of unhappiness and happiness
不快乐的根源，而快乐
often comes from does your vision of
往往来自于你对
your future self match where you are
未来自我的憧憬是否与你
today can you see that path whether
现在的处境相符。你能看到那条路吗？无论
that's finances whether it's Health
是财务还是健康，
they're all very similar
这些都是非常相似的
Journeys and when people can't see the
旅程。当人们看不到
vision of their future self and they
自己未来的愿景，也看不到
can't see how to get there they get
如何实现它时，他们就会感到
upset and what we've tried to
沮丧。我们努力
do is unfuck people's future which is an
做的就是“拯救人们的未来”（unfuck people's future），这是
expression we use which which is a way
我们常用的一个表达方式，它
which is a A mimetic or a meme or just a
是一种模仿、一种梗，或者只是一个
short phraseology to help people
简短的短语，旨在帮助人们
understand we understand that you feel
理解。我们理解你感觉
like you can't get to where you want to
自己无法到达你想去的地方，
get to but there are options to do it
但其实有很多方法可以做到。 我
and I think people are immensely
认为人们
grateful for that in general if you're
普遍对此非常感激。如果你
on a mission to help people unfuck their
致力于帮助人们摆脱困境，
future can you explain to me
能否具体解释一下，
chance of [__] their future from a
从宏观角度来看，哪些因素有可能毁掉他们的未来？
macro perspective and when I say macro
说到宏观，
we have to pause and just Define what I
我们得停下来，先定义一下“宏观”这个词的含义。我理解的宏观是指
the word macro I mean big picture yeah
大局，也就是从宏观的角度来看待问题。
perspective so from a big picture
所以，从宏观的
perspective what are the things that
角度来看，哪些因素有
stand a chance of [__] my future okay
可能毁掉我的未来？
so and we can we can dig into why these
我们可以深入探讨这些
things have occurred but generally
事情发生的原因，但总的来说，
speaking wages in real terms adjusted
经通胀调整后的实际工资几
decades so nobody's getting richer if
十年来都没有上涨，所以没有人变得更富有。如果
you're an American you have this
你是美国人，你耳濡目染着“
powerful meme which is the American
美国梦”这个强大的概念，
dream but that is not a reality for most
但这对于大多数人来说并非现实。
people the reality is you grind it
现实是，你辛辛苦苦工作，
out your savings are not worth what you
你的积蓄却远不如你预期。
you're older living in a nice house none
你曾憧憬着退休后能享受加勒比海的豪华游轮生活，住在漂亮的房子里，但这些都不
of that is true and it's because wages
是真的。原因就在于工资
haven't gone up so okay so let's cut
没有上涨。那么，我们来看看一个
to somebody who's in their 30s now
三十多岁的人…… 现在，
because this is the really important
因为这确实是非常重要的
cohort I think for this
一代人，我认为
they can't afford to buy a house if I go
他们买不起房。如果我回顾一下
back to when I was 30 I bought a house
我30岁的时候，我在伦敦买了一套房子，那是个
in a good area and it was three and a
不错的地段，房子很漂亮，价格是我
half time salary yes I was in finance I
年薪的三倍半。是的，我当时在金融行业，
was earning a high salary you can't buy
收入很高。
anything for three and a half times your
三倍半的年薪根本买不到任何东西。
salary now that same place if I took the
现在，如果我换成
same kind of young investment banker
同样水平的年轻投资银行家，
salary is probably eight or 10 times so
薪水可能是现在的八倍甚至十倍，也就是说，
just buy your first
买第一套房子的成本翻了三倍。
house so what is a house first it's your
那么，房子到底是什么呢？它关乎你的
quality of life particularly you know in
生活质量，尤其是在
England the UK uh in the UK sorry in the
英国——呃，抱歉，在
US we're home buyers you know we think
美国——我们都是购房者，我们把
of our home as our Castle it's it's like
房子看作是我们的城堡，它就像是
the thing that solidifies our
巩固我们
security but you know if you're in
安全感的堡垒。但你知道，
Germany for example they don't they rent
比如在德国，人们并不这样认为，他们租房。
but if we think about the mindset of
但如果我们从
owning a house it's an asset that you
拥有房产的角度来看，它是一种资产，你
can then pass on or you can sell if you
可以把它传承下去，或者在
need to and an asset
需要的时候卖掉。而资产
is really a future Savings Plan it's
实际上就是未来的储蓄计划。
something you save now that in the
现在存钱是为了
future you can consume you can buy stuff
将来消费，为了买东西，
with but what you're doing is for the
但对于
average 35y old the average Millennial
平均35岁（千禧一代平均36
is 36 years
岁）的人来说，
old they can't afford to buy the house
他们买不起房，
so therefore their future self is
所以未来的自己会更
poorer if they think of how much of the
穷。想想看，他们
stock market they can buy they can buy
能用这些钱买多少股票，能买的东西就
less with that money they have less
更少了。他们的积蓄更少，背负着
University so they don't have the
大学债务，所以他们没有
ability to get out of this trap and then
能力摆脱这种困境。
what we are finding is because of this
我们发现，正因为如此，
they're having to live with other people
他们不得不和别人合租
into their
到
30s they're having to they don't have
30多岁，他们没有
kids and they don't get married and
孩子，也没有结婚。
these numbers have collap since 1983
这些数字自1983年以来一直在
you've seen these numbers come down from
下降。独居（
could get your job get yourself an
找到工作，租个
apartment has gone from 80% to 62%
公寓）的人数比例从80%下降到62%，
you're seeing the marriage rate Harve
结婚率下降，
you're seeing um the home ownership rate
房屋拥有率
go from 50% to
从50%下降到
30% these are all expressions of the
30%。所有这些都是
same problems which is people know their
同一个问题的体现，那就是人们意识到……
future is [__] and they can feel it
未来一片黯淡，他们能感受到这一点，
they have a sense of of desperation you
他们感到绝望。你
see then the same cohort of kids in
看，同一批人到了
their 30s doing two jobs three jobs four
三十多岁，却身兼两三份甚至四份工作。
jobs that's not because they want to
这并非出于自愿，
nobody wants to work 12-hour days seven
没人愿意每周七天、每天工作12小时，而是迫不得已。
to and their parents the Baby Boomers
他们的父母，也就是
who are in their 70s and retiring never
七十多岁、即将退休的婴儿潮一代，从未经历过这种境况。
had that they were the richest
他们是
generation in the world had ever seen so
世界上最富有的一代。所以，
this is the first generation that won't
这是第一代不如
be as rich as their parents and that's a
父母富有的人。这很
weird thing because we're all used to
奇怪，因为我们都习惯了
human progress the American dream if the
人类的进步，习惯了美国梦。如果
American dream is well you never be as
美国梦的定义是：你永远无法像
wealthy as your parents and they were
你的父母那样富有，而他们只是
middle class people and I'm now less
中产阶级，而我现在却不如
well off than them that's kind of [__]
他们富裕，这真是太糟糕了。
so look here's some stats about a
所以，这里有一些关于
30-year-old today versus a 30-year-old
如今30岁人群与1983年30岁人群的统计数据。
1983 85% of
1983年，30岁的人群中有85%
them lived on their own they could
独自生活，他们
afford a house or an apartment to rent
买得起房子或公寓。
or to buy now it's 64% so people living
现在租房或买房的比例是64%，所以人们
having to live with other people
不得不与他人合住。
marriage rates they've gone from 80% of
结婚率从
30-y olds in 1983 who were married to
1983年30岁人群中80%的已婚人士下降到
now kids having kids gone from
现在的47%。生育率从
60% to
60%下降到
32% population growth is collapsing
32%。人口增长率正在崩溃，
because people can't afford it and H
因为人们负担不起。30
ownership for a 30-year-old has gone
岁人群的房屋拥有率
from 50% to
从50%下降到
32% it just shows that dramatic change
32%。这表明几十年来发生了巨大的变化，
and why each generation has found it
也解释了为什么每一代人都
more and more difficult to be like their
越来越难以像他们的
parents so I am 30 years oldish yeah I
父母那样生活。我今年30岁左右，是的，我
like to hang on to 30 for as long as I
希望尽可能长时间地保持30岁的状态。
um what advice would you give to someone
你会给像
like me that's my age or maybe even
我这样年龄的人，或者更
younger you know mid 20s as to how to
年轻的人​​，比如20多岁的人，什么建议？如何
play the game over the coming years to
应对未来的人生，才能
make sure that I don't find myself in a
确保自己不会陷入不得不
position where I'm having to work two
打两份
jobs I'm poor I don't have assets I
工、贫穷、没有资产、
don't have anything to show for it like
一无所有等境地。
if you take it right back to being like
这又回到了原点，比如说
maybe let's say a 20-year- old to 25y
一个20到25
old how do you play the game and when I
岁的人，该如何玩转这个游戏？当我
think about this I'm thinking like
思考这个问题时，我想到的是
wealth creation how to then preserve my
创造财富，然后如何保住
wealth like what's the game so the first
财富，这游戏的规则是什么？
part of the game is income okay without
游戏的第一步是收入。没有
income you don't have the cash to do the
收入，你就没有钱去做
other things to invest or to look for
其他事情，比如投资或寻找
opportunities so first thing is income
机会。所以，收入是首要的。
but even that's changing and how we earn
但即使是收入也在变化，我们
incomes these days you know it used to
现在赚钱的方式也不同了。你知道，以前
be you go and work for a big firm you
你去一家大公司工作，
get paid you get the benefit that's all
拿工资，享受福利，一切都变了，
going and nobody wants to do it so you
没人愿意再那样做了。所以你
kind of end up having to be a
最终不得不成为
entrepreneur work two or three different
企业家，同时做两三份不同的工作。
things the point being if your 20s do
关键是，如果你在20多岁的时候
all of that work day and night really do
日夜不停地工作，尽可能
as many things learn as much as you can
多地学习，尽可能多地
fail as often as possible what about
失败，那么20多岁的
work life balance in your 20s [__]
工作生活平衡怎么办？去他的，
it because that's the time to put in the
因为那是
hard work your work life balance
努力工作的时期。工作生活平衡
actually comes out
实际上是
later I'm a big believer in yes if
以后才会出现的。我坚信，如果
you're straight out of University go
你刚从大学毕业，就应该去
traveling for a year or two you know
旅行一两年。 要知道，这不仅能
that a gets rid of the pent up need but
消除压抑的需求，
also gives you a much broader
还能让你拥有比之后
perspective on the world than any other
任何事都更广阔的世界视野。
life after that you get your head down
之后，你可能会埋头苦干，一直
and you get your head down probably to
到
mid-30s okay so what when you say get my
35岁左右。那么，你说埋头苦干是什么意思呢？
down I'm guessing one of the most
我猜，人生
important things in that season of your
那个阶段最重要的事之一
life is knowledge acquisition yeah and
就是获取知识。
then if that's true then the next
如果真是这样，那么下一个
question is what type of knowledge
问题就是：我应该获取什么样的知识才能为
for wealth in the future because I could
未来的财富打下基础？我可以
go acquire knowledge of you know how to
去学习如何
clean a toilet or how to uh be a
清洁厕所，或者如何成为一名
gardener but what what is the most high
园丁，但
returning knowledge for me it is firstly
对我来说，回报最高的知识是什么呢？首先，
be an expert on something okay and then
成为某个领域的专家，然后
possible Right be that expert because
尽可能多地涉猎。成为专家，因为
somebody will pay you for that at least
至少目前会有人为此付费。
for the time being and we'll talk about
我们以后再讨论
how the world may change in the future
世界可能会如何变化，
but for the time being if you're an
但就目前而言，无论你是什么领域的
expert in whatever it may be whether
专家，无论
it's driving a taxi or whether it's a
是开出租车还是
computer scientist doesn't matter be an
计算机科学，都无关紧要，要做
expert compete with yourself day and
专家，日夜与自己竞争。
night to be the best that you can so at
尽你所能做到最好，这样
least it's going to give you the chance
至少能给你一个
to earn some money okay so just to drill
赚钱的机会。好的，在
down on that before we continue to move
我们继续之前，先深入探讨一下：
forward how does one become an expert
一个人如何才能成为专家？比如，
like what are the like how do I have to
我需要做些什么才能
show up to become an expert you're an
成为专家？你
expert on many of okay so this to me is
在许多领域都是专家。好的，对我来说，
there's a trick that I learned and it's
我学到了一个技巧，
called manifesting your own
叫做“显化你的
destiny and what you do is what I've
命运”。我一直以来都是这么做的：
always done my whole life is I envisage
想象自己未来
myself five or 10 years in the
五到十年的样子，我想成为什么样的人。然后环顾四周，问问自己：我想要拥有什么？这是
what are the things that I want to have
我对
Future Vision of myself as opposed to
自己未来的愿景，而不是那种
the 30 40 year path it's too difficult
三十年四十年的目标，因为那太难了。先给自己
give it five years where do I want to be
五年时间，想想五年后我想在哪里。
in five years okay and you look around
好的，然后你展望
that future world and you think okay
未来的世界，思考：
well how would have I got here you know
我是如何走到今天的？比如，
if I've built a business cleaning
如果我建立了一家清洁
windows and I've got 20 people working
窗户的公司，有20个员工，
for me well how did I get there well I
我是如何做到的？我必须
would have had to have figured out okay
弄清楚：
how do I make this scale how do I employ
我如何扩大规模？我如何……
people how do I train them to have the
如何雇佣员工？如何培训他们达到
right standards all of that you ask
合适的标准？所有这些，你都要问问
yourself your question of what that
自己，成功是什么样子？然后
like and you kind of deconstruct it and
你要把它拆解开来，再
go back and make it happen so you
回过头来，努力实现它。所以你要从
fiveyear reality so window cleaner with
五年后的实际情况出发，进行逆向工程。比如，我是一家拥有
20 employees I need to learn management
20名员工的擦窗公司，我需要学习管理
skills I need to learn how to clean a
技能，需要学习如何擦
window accounting accounting I need to
窗，需要
learn probably marketing yeah so that I
学习会计，可能还需要学习市场营销，这样我
can spread the message of my business I
才能更好地推广我的业务。我
probably need to learn potentially like
可能还需要学习
how to speak like public speaking
演讲技巧，比如公开演讲，
because that's sales so I need to I need
因为那是销售的一部分。所以我需要
to learn sales technology you know what
学习销售技巧，比如
what um solvents detergents that people
人们使用的溶剂和清洁剂，以及
using what are the ways of doing it more
更
efficiently and faster so I can beat the
高效、更快捷的清洁方法，这样我才能击败
competitor oh so I might go and work for
竞争对手。哦，所以我可能会去
a big window cleaning company to see how
一家大型擦窗公司工作，看看
they do it to try and see the
他们是怎么做的，看看
opportunity in what they're not doing
他们有哪些不足之处，
yeah or even somebody who manufactures
或者去一家
stuff for that sector it can be anything
为这个行业生产产品的公司工作。任何能让
where you can glean knowledge to give
你获得知识，从而获得
yourself an unfair advantage
竞争优势的地方都可以。
now on podcast it always makes it like
现在在播客里，人们总是把事情说得那么
easy everyone becomes an entrepreneur
简单，好像每个人都成了企业家，
and before you know everybody's Rich
然后很快就发了财。但事实
doesn't work that way but all I'm trying
并非如此。 我正在努力
to do is stack the odds in your favor of
做的，就是增加你实现
future self and you can reverse engineer
未来自我愿景的几率，你可以反向推演，
it so I'm now an expert in whatever I'm
比如我现在是某个领域的专家，
I'm 29 and I'm an expert in window
我29岁，擅长擦窗之类的，而且我涉猎
a generalist in many things you're
广泛。你
saying that's going to enable me to
说的这些能让我开始
start to build wealth in something so
积累财富，从而开启人生的
that I can go to the next season of My
下一个阶段。
so when you become an expert or when you
所以，当你成为专家或者
become good at
擅长
something if you're careful in your
某件事的时候，如果你谨慎
expenditure you will produce excess
支出，就能获得额外的
income right because people are going to
收入，因为人们会为
pay you for your expertise so if you
你的专业知识付费。如果你
manage yourself carefully in those first
在最初几年里谨慎管理
years that excess cash you can then
这些额外的现金，你就可以
choose what to do with it now maybe you
选择如何使用它。也许你
want to build the real business that you
想建立你
wanted to build in the first place the
最初就想建立的真正事业，实现
crazy idea you've had and if if you're
你一直以来的疯狂想法。如果你才
in your 20s you can take the risk and
20多岁，你可以承担风险，把
blow your savings on that crazy
积蓄投入到这个疯狂的
idea because you've actually learned how
想法中，因为你已经
to do build a business already by
通过
building the one that you
建立你
started or you start investing
创办的事业学会了如何创业。或者，你可以开始投资。
now the world of Investments was this
投资的世界是这样的…… 这个
world of weird financial advisors and
世界上充斥着各种奇葩的理财顾问，
they would tell you something like well
他们会告诉你，
you do this and then you're a 25y old in
你这样做，45年后你25岁的时候
45 years time you'll get some money I
就能拿到一笔钱。我的天哪！我
get out of it when I'm 65 years old I
65岁的时候
suddenly get a lump suum that I've spent
突然拿到一笔我毕生
my whole life saving for I don't feel it
积蓄的钱，我能从中得到什么？我根本没感觉。
it's got I've got no emotional attaching
我对
to my pension
我的养老金
plan and I've got real world problems to
计划没有任何情感上的依恋，而且我还有现实生活中的问题要
solve I can't buy a
解决。我买不起
house I can't get married I can't have
房，结不了婚，生不了
kids so I need to solve these in a
孩子。所以我需要在比
shorter time period than my pension my
养老金更短的时间内解决这些问题。我的
pension was suitable for a different
养老金计划是为上
generation that just needed enough after
一代人准备的，他们退休后只需要足够的钱。
they stopped working so I got to solve
所以我必须解决这个问题。
that and the answer is investing then
答案是投资。
most people roll their eyes and go
大多数人会翻白眼，说
really stocks and bonds it's
股票债券？太无聊了。是
boring yeah but the world has changed
啊，但是世界已经改变了，
the world has changed in many many ways
世界在很多方面都发生了变化，
but it's offered us opportunities
但也给我们提供了机会，
whether it's investing in technology
无论是投资科技，还是
investing in crypto that gives us much
投资加密货币，都能
in shorter periods of time okay that's a
在更短的时间内带来更高的回报，简直是不可思议的回报。这简直
magic that's magic for young people it
太神奇了！ 对年轻人来说，投资
may be too risky for their parents but
可能风险太大，父母可能不买账。但
if you're young and you can take some
如果你年轻，又能承担一定
risk okay here's your chance so now you
风险，那么机会来了！现在你
can build a business use some excess
可以创业，利用一些
savings put them in
积蓄进行
Investments now you're on the path so
投资。你已经走上了正轨，接下来我们来谈谈
let's get on to investing then but just
投资。不过，在
before we get on to investing um I was
开始投资之前，我想先分析一下
personas of my audience and I was
我的目标受众的不同类型。我发现他们中的
thinking that some of them are working
一些人现在非常非常努力地工作，比如
cab driver they could be you know doing
出租车司机，或者从事
some sort of manual labor and it feels
体力劳动。他们感觉无论
to them that no matter how hard they
多么
work they still don't have that excess
努力，都没有足够的
income to invest so for those people and
收入进行投资。对于这些人来说，
this is a little bit of a maybe a
这可能是一个有点
contentious question like is there
争议的问题：
something that they're doing wrong as it
他们在投资方面是不是做错了什么？不，投资就是
game and you have to play the
投资，你必须参与其中。
game so okay so maybe you don't have
所以，也许你没有
thousands to
几千美元可以
invest I've seen many many people in
投资，但我见过很多人在
Market like crypto go
加密货币市场
from
从
$500 to
500美元涨到
$500,000 now there's a lot of people who
50万美元。当然，也有很多人
don't either but all I'm saying is the
没有这么多钱。 但我只是想说，
opportunity is there you don't need to
机会就在那里，你不需要
bet your house you don't need to have
孤注一掷，也不需要
huge savings you just need to focus on
巨额积蓄，你只需要专注于
what you're doing understand how to
你正在做的事情，了解如何
manage risks a bit and how to look for
管理风险，以及如何寻找
opportunities and it's the self self
机会。关键在于自我
teing is how do I become that guy who's
提升。比如，如果我今天只有500美元或1000美元，我该如何成为
got a half a million dollar
拥有50万美元投资
portfolio considering I've only got $500
组合的人？这仍然
today or $1,000 today is that possible
可能吗？是的，
still yeah very much so haven't I missed
完全有可能，不是吗？ 错过了
the boat
机会？
no no it's happening again right now in
不不，现在又来了，这次是加密
mean coins this is Fascinating People
货币领域。这太有趣了。人们可能会觉得
watching this will go what a bunch of
这都是
nonsense these are coins tokens we'll
胡说八道，这些只是代币而已，我们以后
talk about blockchain and and this later
再谈区块链之类的东西。
but these are investments based on
但这些投资是基于网络迷
a meme a joke a joke something that
因、笑话、梗，以及一些
grabs attention on the
在互联网上能吸引眼球的东西，
internet and you can bet on those well
你可以押注这些。这是什么意思呢？这其实就是
what is that that's about betting on
押注
attention itself if you think about a
注意力本身。想想像
business like Facebook or Google or any
Facebook、谷歌或者
of these Twitter they're all based on
Twitter这样的公司，它们都是建立在注意力基础上的。
attention and now we can bet on
现在我们可以押注
attention do people find that funny are
注意力，人们觉得这个好笑吗？
months time or six weeks time and we can
六个月后或者六周后他们还会觉得好笑吗？我们可以
bet on this stuff okay this is the super
押注这些东西。好吧，这部分内容非常具有
speculative end but it's also very
投机性，但它也与
cultural it's not about investment
文化息息相关。这与投资
bankers it's not about Gatekeepers it's
银行家无关，也与守门人无关，而是
about you pitting yourself thinking is
关于你自己去思考：
this going to catch on viral and if it
这会不会爆红？如果会，它会不会
is is it going to grow bigger now some
发展壮大？有些
of those might do a thousand X in six
东西可能在六个月内涨个一千倍，
months now 99% go to zero but all I'm
但99%会跌到谷底。我只是
saying is returns are
想说，回报是
there and then you've got different
存在的，而且
levels of return if we look at
回报水平也各不相同。 看看
Bitcoin well actually let's compare it
比特币，其实我们来把它和标普500指数比较一下。标普500
important number later what's the S&amp;P
指数稍后会很重要。标普500指数是什么？它
500 that's the US Stock Market it's the
是美国股市的代表，是衡量
broadest measure of the stock market and
股市最广泛的指标。
you can buy shares in it now that grows
你现在可以购买它的股票，它的年增长率
about 10% a year 11% a year so let's
大约是10%到11%。
imagine you've got your $1,000 well 11%
假设你有1000美元，年增长率是11%，
a year it's going to take you a [__]
你需要很
long time to make any money right so it
长时间才能赚到钱，对吧？所以
is not worth your time the financial
不值得你花时间。理财
advisers will say yes you must do this
顾问会说，你必须
start now I'm like I'm sorry it's just
现在就开始投资。但我会说，抱歉，它
not going to change your life okay then
不会改变你的生活。然后
we go to technology stocks NASDAQ does
我们来看看科技股，纳斯达克指数的
about 18% a year okay that's starting to
年增长率大约是18%。这开始有点意思了，
add up because these numbers compound
因为这些数字会复利增长。
after a while you know it goes from a
你知道，它从
th000 to
1000涨到
1,200 and then you know it's another 20%
1200，然后又涨了20%，再在
on top of that 20% these numbers add up
这20%的基础上再涨20%。这些数字累积起来
fast
很快。
Bitcoin since
比特币自
2011 been
2011年以来……
145% a year even with it falling 80%
即使期间三次下跌80%，年收益率仍然能达到145%，
145% A year as long as you're in it long
只要你坚持足够长的时间，就能获得145%的收益。
enough okay now that's really starting
现在，这真的开始带来
to pay off and then as you get slightly
回报了。然后，随着你进行
more
更多
speculative I take a bit more risk in
投机性投资，承担更多风险，
things well the returns go up but they
收益会上升，但
become riskier so once you start moving
风险也会增加。一旦你开始进入
into that world okay this is a whole
那个领域，那就完全是
different world now now the guy with
另一个世界了。现在，拥有
$1,000 can get rich what about buying a
1000美元的人可以致富，那么
house because I think most people think
买房呢？因为我认为大多数人认为，
the minute they get some excess income
一旦有了额外的收入——
and no for sure when I say most people
不，我敢肯定，我说的是大多数人，大概
it's like 95% of people that walk the
95%的人都认为
streets think that the minute you get
——一旦有了
some excess income you should take it
额外的收入，就应该把它
and put it in a savings account and buy
存入储蓄账户，然后买
your first house get your first
第一套房子，申请第一笔
mortgage now as a strategy for wealth
抵押贷款，以此作为积累财富的策略。但这真的是
is that a good approach no because it's
个好方法吗？当然不是。因为
creation people think of houses as like
人们把房子当作
an asset but in the end you barely ever
资产，但最终你几乎不会
will sell your house to take the money
卖掉房子来取出钱。
out you might downsize later in life if
你可能会在晚年
absolutely needed you might sell it but
绝对必要的时候缩小住房面积，那时可能会卖掉房子，但
generally speaking your house is the
总的来说，你的房子就是你的
lifestyle bank now that is super
生活银行。 这非常
important and I think it is the most
重要，我认为最
important trade of all is the lifestyle
重要的交易就是生活
bank so what do you do this All For You
银行。那么，你这种“
Want lifestyle so do you sacrifice your
随心所欲”的生活方式到底是怎么回事？难道你要牺牲
future self having more money by having
未来的自己，为了
a house and having security earlier I
更早拥有房子和保障而牺牲未来吗？我
would argue those days are gone what do
认为那种日子已经一去不复返了。什么
you mean so I could do it because it was
意思？我以前能做到，因为房子是
three times income yeah so a house was
收入的三倍。是的，房子
not expensive for me so I could stop
对我来说并不贵，所以我可以
paying it off a bit sooner and it became
早点停止还款，这对我来说
not a big deal but now your mortgage is
也不是什么大问题。但现在，你的房贷
likely
可能相
huge amount versus your income you'll
对于你的收入来说是一笔巨款，你余生都要用来
off and most of the time you're just
还贷，而且大部分时间你只是在还
paying off the interest so you don't
利息。所以
actually you're not getting anywhere you
实际上你什么都没得到，你
don't own that house anything goes wrong
并不真正拥有那套房子，一旦出了什么问题，
the bank takes it away from you so
银行就会收回它。所以
you've got to get more
你必须更好地
control of your life and that is by
掌控自己的生活，而这可以通过积累不断增长的
having savings that are growing then you
储蓄来实现。这样你
can make the choice you know let's say
才能做出选择。
that example of the person gone from
比如说，有人从
$1,000 to5 00,000
1000美元变成了50万美元，
maybe on Route they say well I'm going
也许他们会说：“我要
to take some money off the table and put
拿出一些钱存入
it in my lifestyle bank and I'm going to
我的生活银行。”
buy a house that's what I've done my
买房是我
whole career and I find the lifestyle
整个职业生涯都在做的事情，我发现它能带来一种生活方式上的
bank that that's the reward because now
满足感，这就是回报。因为现在的情况是，
it's like okay nobe you can take my
好吧，你随时可以把我的
house away so if I'm trying
房子拿走。所以，如果我想
to build
积累
wealth buying a house is not a good idea
财富，买房并不是一个好主意，
it's not the best approach to take to
它不是积累财富的最佳途径。
build wealth you're telling me that it's
你是说，这
actually not about psychology and about
实际上与心理和
emotion the house and it's not about
情感无关，与房子无关，也与
making myself wealthy um I I wanted to
让自己变得富有无关吗？嗯，我想
read some of the comments that people
看看人们
often post when we talk about these
在我们讨论这些话题时经常发表的一些评论，
subjects because I think you're
因为我认为你
probably the guy to address some of them
可能是最能解答其中一些问题的人。
I bought a house and it's the best thing
我买了一套房子，这是
I ever did it launched my mindset in New
我做过的最棒的事情，它让我的思维方式焕然一新。
Directions remember that having your own
记住，拥有自己的
space has profound psychological impact
空间会对心理产生深远的影响，
and can be lifechanging in for some that
对于一些
don't live in a healthy environment I
生活在不健康环境中的人来说，它可以改变人生。我
guess that speaks to your point about um
想这正印证了你关于买房
it being a psychological but you would
是一种心理因素的观点。但
also get the same feeling if you rented
如果你租了一套房子，而且房子位置
that was in a nice place and you knew
很好，
that you know your rent was Secure it
你知道你的租金很稳定，
wasn't going to go up whatever it was I
不会上涨，你也会有同样的感觉。我
don't think there's any difference to
不认为这有什么区别。
that as long as you can feel that you've
只要你感到
got security you can take risk and do
安全，你就可以承担风险并做
other things I purchased a house in 2014
其他事情。我在2014年买了一套房子，
and I sold it seven years later for 66k
七年后以6.6万英镑的
profit um I've put a large amount of the
利润卖掉了。我把大部分净值投入
Equity into a financial Investment
了银行的金融投资
Portfolio with my bank and it's been
组合，但至今为止已经
down 2% since I also put some money into
下跌了2%。我还
different shares based on war buffit
根据War Buffit
strategy and that's now up 18% a friend
策略投资了一些股票，现在这些股票上涨了18%。
of mine also lost about 30 to 40K on
我的一个朋友在股市投资中也损失了大约3万到4万英镑。
investing in the stock market you have
你必须
to be careful I don't think there's a
小心。我认为没有绝对
correct solution some house purchases do
正确的解决方案。有些房产投资收益
purchases do amazing and some people
惊人，有些人确实能获得回报。
make returns as a as a sentiment I often
我经常
see about buying a house yes and you
看到有人这样说，买房确实能带来丰厚的回报。是的，你
know we're here today the UK there's a
知道，我们今天在英国，有一种很流行的
big idea about buying two or three
想法是买两三
houses getting a mortgage renting them
套房子，申请抵押贷款，然后
out using the cash flow to pay for the
出租，用租金收入来支付
other one right that's a lot of people's
另一套房子的房贷。这确实是很多人
dream portfolio idea you know I've
梦寐以求的投资组合。我
rented out houses in the past generally
过去也出租过房子。一般来说，
it's if you're not in a big city like
如果你…… 在像
London it's generally often a terrible
伦敦这样的大城市，这通常不是什么好
business because you got to repair them
生意，因为你需要维修房屋，还有
there's a lot goes on headache headache
很多其他问题，比如
tenants yeah it's you know PE people
租户问题，让人头疼。你知道，私募股权投资的人
think it's easy money I just I just do
觉得这是轻松赚钱的机会，好像什么都
nothing and it all makes money it there
不用做就能赚钱。但
is no easy money in this world and
世界上没有轻松赚钱的途径，而且
there's risk right because that little
风险也很大。因为那层抵押
pyramid of mortgages are all backed by
贷款的金字塔结构都建立在
your income being a to P pay the
你的收入之上，你得先偿还
mortgage on the first house if you lose
第一套房子的抵押贷款。如果你失业了，
happens then it becomes problematic
问题就来了。
because if you're losing your job maybe
如果你失业了，也许
the economy is slow and other people are
经济不景气，其他人也
losing their job and suddenly before you
失业了，突然之间，所有
know none of these mortgages are getting
这些抵押贷款都无法
paid and guess what you don't know any
偿还。你猜怎么着？你根本不知道
of the stuff houses are not a safe
这些。房子并不是安全的
investment they feel safe because the
投资。人们之所以觉得安全，是因为
price doesn't go up and down every day
房价不会每天波动，不会出现
it's not on the screen it's not on
在屏幕上，也不会出现在
CNBC but they're IL liquid which means
CNBC的报道中。它们的流动性很强，这意味着
they don't often trade but sometimes
它们不经常交易。但有时，
something happens in that equation
这种等式中会出现一些问题，
either the price goes down or your
要么是房价下跌，要么是你
ability to pay that mortgage goes and
无力偿还抵押贷款，
then the whole thing collapses in
然后整个体系会在
seconds and 2008 was that double
几秒钟内崩溃。2008年就是这样，
everyone lost their jobs so they
每个人都失业了。 所以他们
couldn't pay the mortgage and the house
还不起房贷，
prices collaps and so I don't think
房价暴跌，因此我不认为
houses are the paner they're not the
房子是最佳选择，它们并非
perfect answer yes they can be real
完美答案。没错，它们可以成为投资标的，但
estate is a decent opportunity and we'll
房地产是一个不错的机会。我们会
talk about debasement and currency and
讨论货币贬值和货币体系的
how that all works and real estate is
运作机制，房地产还可以，
okay it's certainly not the best but but
当然不是最好的选择。但是，
you know yes if you're rich and you can
你知道，如果你很富有，可以
own these things without
不用贷款就能拥有这些房产，
mortgages you can be the Duke of
你可以成为
Westminster and own half of London and
威斯敏斯特公爵，拥有半个伦敦，然后
just collect rent you can do that for X
只收租金，你可以这样做
generations and be rich forever I get it
几代人，永远富有。我明白，
but most of us don't get into that
但我们大多数人不会陷入那种
situation my brother who has been an
境地。我的兄弟，他做了
investment banker for about 10 years now
大约10年的投资银行家，现在
works in my company in my fund he said
在我公司的基金工作。
to me when I was young when it comes to
我年轻的时候，他告诉我，说到
creating wealth what you want to do is
创造财富，你应该
focus on games that very few people can
专注于那些只有极少数人能
play but you have a unique advantage in
参与，但你却拥有独特优势的游戏。
because he because everyone can buy a
因为每个人都能
house so the you can you should assume
买房，所以你应该预料到，这样
that the returns from doing it aren't
做的回报不会很
going to be amazing so he was like go
惊人。所以他说，
find a game that you have high leverage
去找一个你能高杠杆、
you have a unfair Advantage be the
拥有不公平优势的游戏，成为
expert in something yeah be the expert
某个领域的专家。 成为某个领域的专家，
in something where you because of your
凭借你的
knowledge your expertise your experience
知识、专业技能、经验和人
your contacts you can play that game but
脉，你可以玩转这个领域，而
very few other people can because that's
其他人却很少能做到，因为这才是
where you'll yield your highest returns
你获得最高回报的地方。
and I always thought about that just
我一直都这么想，
a house so logically you can go okay
逻辑上就是：如果每个人都能玩这个游戏，如果你期望获得高回报，那就别玩，因为回报会非常低。我告诉你，每个人刚有点收入的时候，做的第一件事就是买房。所以，从逻辑上讲，除非
returns unless I get lucky unless I get
我运气爆棚，否则买房不会给我带来最佳回报。除非我运气好到爆棚，
in an area and then they build a bloody
在某个地方买了个谷仓，然后旁边建了个
Whole Foods next door and it becomes the
全食超市，它就成了
the center of the world um which isn't
世界中心——嗯，这种情况发生的
again the probability is still not great
概率仍然很低。
so what do you think of that as a theory
你觉得这个理论怎么样？
well the same Theory as I said
正如我所说，同样的理论是，
is be an expert in something and you can
成为某个领域的专家，你就能
find more opportunity if you're just a
找到更多机会。如果你只是个
generalist it's really hard because
通才，那就很难了，因为
you're competing against average people
你要和
doing average things right if you're
做着普通事情的普通人竞争。如果你
just working in an insurance office
只是在保险公司上班，
I mean there's thousands of people plus
我的意思是，那里有成千上万的人。
you're competing with AI you know H how
你知道，你是在和人工智能竞争，你该如何才能
within that how do you become an expert
在这个领域有所作为？你又该如何成为专家呢？
now you could teach yourself okay if I
你可以自学，好吧，如果我
don't mind this industry and I think I
不介意这个行业，而且我认为我
know it maybe I need to learn management
了解它，也许我需要学习管理
skills maybe I spend all the time
技能，也许我应该花所有时间
listening to podcast and learning
听播客学习
management maybe it's and that's I can
管理，也许这样我就能
then manifest my destiny but as you
实现我的梦想。但正如你
say doing something other people aren't
所说，做别人没
doing is a superpower to know what's
做过的事情是一种超能力，要知道什么才是
really interesting with that is this
真正有趣的。
idea of becoming an expert um I think is
成为专家的想法，我认为
critically important but then there's
至关重要。但
this other step I found which is knowing
我发现还有另一个步骤，那就是知道将
what Market to apply your expertise to
你的专业知识应用到哪个市场才能
to yield the greatest return and the
获得最大回报。
very simple analogy I'll give you is for
我给你举个简单的例子：在
the first portion of my career I was I
我职业生涯的早期，我
became an expert in social media now
成为了社交媒体专家。
with that skill set and expertise you
有了这项技能和专业知识，
can do a number of things you can help a
你可以做很多事情，比如帮助一家
fashion company sell more dresses and
时装公司卖出更多衣服，
that will yield X return a smaller
这会带来X的回报，回报较小。但在
return then in the second portion of my
我
career I realized that that expertise
职业生涯的后期，我意识到，如果我将这项专业知识
applied it to helping public companies
应用于帮助上市公司在
tell their story before their IPO
IPO前讲述他们的故事，那么它的价值最高，也最稀缺，
because the variance and outcome for the
因为差异性……
public company that I was applying my
我运用
social media expertise to was billions
社交媒体专长为一家上市公司带来的结果是数十亿美元。
so in the second sort of sort of era of
所以在
my career I worked with companies that
我职业生涯的第二个阶段，我与即将上市的公司合作，这些公司
could be you know their market cap could
市值可能
be 1 billion or if they were really good
达到10亿美元，或者如果他们非常擅长
at telling their story in a world where
讲述自己的故事——在这个
retail investors are now so interesting
散户投资者如今
to everyone because of Wall Street bets
因华尔街投机而备受关注的世界里——
their market cap could be three billion
他们的市值可能达到30亿美元。
then that means they would pay me seven
这意味着他们会为我的技能支付我七位
figures for my skill set and I often
数的报酬。我经常
think about it you think about the stock
思考这个问题。想想
market if you put a company on the stock
股市，如果你把一家公司放在
market in London it's valued at let's
伦敦股市上市，它的估值可能是
say 1 million if you put it on the stock
100万美元；如果把它放在
market in America the same company is
美国股市，同一家公司的
valued at four million the same company
估值就变成了400万美元。
if you think of your skills like that
如果你这样看待你的技能，
where are you applying your skills to re
你会在哪里运用它们来
re reap the highest return let's go back
获得最高的回报呢？让我们回到那位
to the window cleaner who's now decided
决定创业的擦窗工，他现在
got 20 people yeah okay so he's now got
有20名员工。好吧，他现在面临着
the hassle of managing all these people
管理所有这些员工的麻烦，
they turn out sick and then this happens
他们会生病，然后又会发生其他事情……
and then the customers are unhappy so
客户不满意，所以
maybe the right answer is to create a
也许正确的解决办法是创建一个
program to train other people to build
培训项目，让其他人也能建立
their own window cleaning
自己的窗户清洁
companies free yourself from the rat
公司。这样
race and build this business you'll make
你就能摆脱朝九晚五的竞争，建立自己的事业。这样
more money doing that than you will from
做肯定比你亲自擦窗户赚得多得多，
because you're going up the knowledge
因为你的知识
curve the further up the more of an
水平会不断提高，
expert you are and there's two things
你就越专业。
that people need to think about you
人们需要考虑两件事：
either have a very broad market for
要么你的市场非常广泛，比如像
something candy
糖果
bars well then you've got to sell
棒这样的产品，那么你就必须
massive scale and it's really hard or
大规模销售，这非常困难；要么
you go through an area that has a very
你专注于一个拥有非常
specific group of users buyers
特定用户群体（
whatever and particularly ones that have
尤其是那些
a lot of money so let's go back to the
有钱人）的领域。我们再回到
house idea again the guy speculating on
房子的例子，说说那些投机倒把的人。有
houses so there's two house
两种
speculators there's the guy or girl
投机者：一种是四处
who's hustling and renting them out
奔波，
finding the cheap bargain doing them up
寻找便宜的房子，装修后出租，
renting getting the cash flow doing
赚取现金流；另一种是花
buying a place for 10 million making it
1000万美元买一套房子，把它改造成
Ultra Luxury and selling it to the
超级豪华住宅，然后卖给
billionairs and flipping it for
亿万富翁，再以
50 that the difference in the turns is
5000万美元的价格转手卖掉。这两种方式的利润差距很大。 令人
staggering why because one group is
震惊的是，为什么会有这样的结果？因为有一部分人对
price insensitive in fact the more
价格不敏感，事实上，
expensive it is the more they want it
价格越高他们越想要；而
the other group is trying to compete
另一部分人则试图
with everybody else you know the two the
与所有人竞争，你知道，比如
two-bedroom apartment in the city right
市中心的两居室公寓，
there's thousands of those being done up
成千上万套公寓正在装修
and sold and everything else so to your
出售等等。所以，正如你
point earlier the returns are less but
之前提到的，回报会更少。但是，
no if you're doing super
如果你做的是超
highend then there is a defined group of
高端清洁，那么就会有一个明确的
buyers of which you probably know them
买家群体，你可能都认识他们。
all yeah
是的，就我
personally you can count to their taste
个人而言，你可以了解他们的品味，
and they have unlimited money that's the
而且他们财力雄厚，这才是关键所在，不是吗？关键在于
big thing isn't it's like who you're
你为谁
solving the problem for because you can
解决问题。你可以为
clean like Dorothy's Windows lives in a
住在普利茅斯平房里的多萝西清洁窗户，
bungalow in Plymouth or you can clean
也可以为
Google's windows and there you get a
谷歌清洁窗户，在那里你会获得
bigger contract you get guaranteed work
更大的合同，有稳定的工作，
probably get retain you get more windows
可能还会获得长期合作，有更多的窗户需要
to clean it's still one contract it's
清洁。仍然是一份合同，
still one sell it's the same skill set
仍然是一次销售，需要的
same skill set they're going to pay you
技能也是一样的，他们会付给你
a lot more and and then and so I just
更高的报酬。所以，我
don't think I always find that bit Miss
觉得我们
missing when we talk about like become
谈论成为
an expert but then like who do you sell
专家时，常常忽略了这一点，那就是：你到底要
to and your idea of selling to people
卖给谁？ 你的想法是向那些对
that are more price and
价格更
sensitive and that aren't going to and
敏感、不太愿意购买其他产品的人销售，
less people are trying to sell to or
或者向那些目标客户群体
they're super
非常
defined right like like Tom Bilu who we
明确的人群销售，对吧？就像汤姆·比鲁（Tom Bilu），我们都
both know Tom's a good friend yeah he
知道，汤姆是我的好朋友。他
made his money because there was a rise
发家致富是因为
in high protein ketogenic
高蛋白生酮
foods and it was difficult to have that
食品的兴起，而当时很难找到合适的
snack bar because people still have a
零食棒，因为人们仍然喜欢
sweet tooth but they can't have sugar so
甜食，但又不能摄入糖分。所以
him and his Partners built quest which
他和他的合伙人创立了Quest，
is now everywhere so what you found is a
现在Quest的产品随处可见。所以你发现了一个
trend and this is really really really
趋势，这一点非常非常
important is you find a trending Market
重要：找到一个市场趋势，
where people are
那里的人们的需求没有得到充分
underserved and they'll pay a lot of
满足，而且他们愿意为此支付
money because it's Health it's like
高价，因为健康就像
wealth and health people pay Fortunes in
财富一样，人们在
our industry and so you make a fortune
我们的行业里愿意为健康付出巨额资金。所以你很快就能赚到一大笔钱。当然，
very quickly now now it's a saturated
现在
market so it's not that easy but this is
市场已经饱和了，所以没那么容易。但
the other key key thing is if you've got
另一个关键点是，如果你从零开始，那就
a clean slate do one
做一
thing follow a trend a secular Trend a
件事：追随趋势，追随长期趋势。长期
secular trend is a long-term Trend
趋势是指正在发生的长期趋势，对吧？
everything is being digitized you wrode
一切都在数字化，你写过
that Trend right social media was new
这个趋势，对吧？社交媒体是大约从……开始出现的。
2010 right now it's a saturated market
2010年，市场已经饱和，
and we've got AI coming in but you rode
人工智能也即将到来，但你抓住了
a secular Trend in the hyper
超
acceleration pH phase yeah that's why
加速阶段的长期趋势，没错，这就是
you did well so you look for a trend
你成功的原因。你要寻找一个规模
that's big meaningful and
大、意义深远且
provable and use your skill set in that
可验证的趋势，并运用你的技能去把握它。
we've seen something in America I don't
我们在美国看到了一些变化，我不
know if you just saw the trend finally
知道你是否也注意到了，
the Obesity numbers tick down I didn't
肥胖率终于开始下降了。我之前并不
know that yeah first time in 50 years
知道。是的，这是50年来美国
obesity starts to fall in the
肥胖率首次开始下降，对吧？
US right this is a zic effect and it's
这是一种ZIC效应，也
probably some Diet
可能与饮食有关。
effect my belief is the more people
我认为，人们越是
would take a Zen Pig the more they also
接受Zen Pig（一种饮食疗法），就越会
think about diet and understand that
思考饮食问题，并意识到
something went wrong for them and my
自己的饮食出了问题。我
guess is there is going to be huge
猜测，
healthy eating the other one is in an
健康饮食的趋势将会带来巨大的机遇。另一个机遇是在一个
increasingly Aid driven online digital
日益人工智能驱动的在线数字
world there's two things that are going
世界中，将会出现两件事：一是
to happen one the rise of digital
数字
communities you see this in what you do
社区的兴起，你在工作中看到了这一点，我在工作中也
I see it what I do they become more and
看到了这一点。
important uh communities online they're
在线社区变得越来越重要，
meaningful for people the other is the
对人们来说意义重大。二是
entire flip side I spend 12 hours down
完全相反的情况，我每天花12个小时在Zoom上。 对
valuable thing to me nature nature and
我来说，最宝贵的东西就是自然和
experiences so let's say you're that
体验。假设你
person that loves the outdoors well
热爱户外活动，那就
start a guiding company because your job
开一家向导公司吧，因为你的工作
is not going to be taken by the robots
不会很快被机器人取代。
anytime soon sure you'll have drones
当然，你会带着无人机，帮你给
guests you're going with or or look for
客人拍照，或者寻找
animals or whatever you're doing you'll
动物等等，你
be leveraging technology but your job
会利用科技，但你的工作
will not be
不会被
replaced okay what I'm about to say is a
取代。接下来我要说的是我刚才听到的一些
mish mash of ideas that came to mind as
想法，它们有点杂乱无章。
you were speaking the first one was how
第一个想法是，
do I spot a trend and when I say that I
我该如何发现趋势？我的意思是，在当下，这种趋势给人的
mean how does it feel in the moment
感觉如何？
because the trends that you capitalized
因为你和我曾经抓住的那些趋势，在当时都会给人一种特定的感觉。
here I'm talking about like how
我指的是
disruptive they are contrarian what
它们的颠覆性、反潮流性，
people will say to you they'll tell you
人们会怎么说你，他们会说
you're an idiot and then with that as
你是个傻瓜。此外，
well you talked about um
你还提到，在
how right now in the world we live in
我们生活的这个世界里，投资
betting on things like nature is a good
自然之类的东西是个好
idea and I actually did a post on my
主意。事实上，我在我的
LinkedIn about exactly this I said my
领英上也专门写过一篇关于这个主题的文章。 我说我的
investment fund is backing two things at
投资基金目前支持两件事：
the moment Ai and Automation and the
人工智能和自动化，以及
exact opposite because I saw this viral
完全相反的事。因为我看到一个爆红的
video of people and I think it was like
视频，视频里的人好像是
a cafe in Amsterdam who come now every
在阿姆斯特丹的一家咖啡馆，每周都去，那里
week no phones allowed they read books
不允许使用手机，人们读书、
and they knit and this Cafe in Amsterdam
织毛衣。这家阿姆斯特丹的咖啡馆现在非常火爆。
is like exploding I'll put the video of
我把这段视频放到大
these people on the screen for everyone
屏幕上让大家都
to see and it made me realize and that
看到，这让我意识到，
that overlap with what a two billionaire
这与我两位亿万富翁
friends of mine said to me in private
朋友私下跟我说的话不谋而合。
they said these are billionaires that
他们说，这些亿万富翁
invest in AI they invest in crypto you
投资人工智能、加密货币（你
probably know one of them and they
可能认识其中一位），他们还
invest in psychedelics they said to me
投资迷幻药。他们告诉我，
if you want to invest right now invest
如果现在想投资，就投资
in AI if you can but if you can't invest
人工智能，如果可以的话；如果不行，就投资
in entertainment and Community because
娱乐和社区。因为
in a world of AI where productivity is
在人工智能时代，生产力
so high and we maybe move towards some
如此之高，我们或许会走向某种
form of universal basic income where the
形式的全民基本收入，
government just hands people money
政府直接给人们发钱，
people are going to have so much free
人们会有很多空闲
time on their hands that they're going
时间，
to need something to do with it so they
需要找点事做。所以他们
he said to me this is why you're seeing
告诉我，这就是为什么现在越来越多的
this rise in people buying football
人购买足球
clubs uh and these sporting franchises
俱乐部和其他体育特许经营权的
because that's one of the that's
原因。 这既是
community and its entertainment at the
社区，也是娱乐，
same time so I throwing all of that at
所以我把所有这些都一股脑儿地抛给
you yes the equal and opposite idea is I
你。是的，与之相反的观点也
think very
很
important I just came back from three
重要。我刚从赞比亚越野回来，在那里待了三个
weeks off-roading in Zambia living on a
星期，住在
tent on the roof of a Toyota Land
丰田陆地巡洋舰车顶上的帐篷里，这辆车
Cruiser that is off-road prepared and
是越野改装过的，我们深入到了
going out into total wilds and I can't
完全的荒野。我无法用语言来形容，在那种状态下，
express how in the present you become
你会变得多么自由，它
how it cleanses your mind from all of
如何让你的思绪从所有
the Clutter all of the things you worry
杂乱无章的事情中解脱出来，所有让你担忧的事情，比如
about the broken car or the whatever's
坏掉的车，或者
going on online the politics it all goes
网上发生的各种事情，政治等等，所有的一切都消失了，所有的一切都
and it all becomes about you wake up
变成了你醒来后要做什么，
who's going to make the coffee who's
谁来煮咖啡，谁来
going to put the fire on who's going to
生火，谁来
do you know and so the more time we
做……你知道的。所以我们
spend online the more we desperately
花在网上的时间越多，我们就越
crave I saw it in the Cayman Islands
渴望……我在我居住的开曼群岛看到了这一点，这
where I live so it's a Caribbean isand
是一个加勒比海岛屿，那
and it was
是
2022 and the world hadn't really
2022年，世界还没有真正
recovered you know there was the high
复苏，你知道，
inflation people were losing jobs
通货膨胀很高，人们失去了工作，
everyone was really uncomfortable with
每个人都对
the economic situation it was painful
经济形势感到非常不安，这对
for a lot of people we're at a record
很多人来说都很痛苦，而我们正处于创纪录的
tourist season I'm like what the hell's
旅游旺季。 我当时就想，这到底是怎么回事？
spending goes down in times like that
在那种情况下，可自由支配的支出会减少。
and I realized holidays had not become
我意识到，假期不再是
discretionary spend they become
可自由支配的支出，而是变成了
necessity as a reaction to work from
必需品。这是
home if you're on your own at home
居家办公的一种反应。如果你独自在家为
working for a startup or a company or
一家初创公司或企业工作，或者
doing whatever it kind of feels a bit
做任何事情，都会感到有些
lonely and so you start seeking out
孤独。于是，你开始寻找
like-minded people who have like-minded
志同道合的人，他们有着相似的
Pursuits now that could be sporting
爱好。这些爱好可以是支持某个运动
teams it could also
队，也可以
be Chihuahua lovers because you happen
是吉娃娃爱好者，因为你碰巧养了
to have a chihuaha and you love it and
一只吉娃娃，而且你很爱它。
you will talk to other people around the
你会和世界各地的人交流，
world you now have no borders this is
现在你不再受地域限制。这就是
this buudy idea of the network states
网络社交的理念，
where you can create large groups of
你可以创建庞大的
Interest so if you look at the largest
兴趣群体。如果你看看
group of interest in all of social media
所有社交媒体中最大的兴趣群体，
it's actually crypto why because we feel
它实际上是加密货币。为什么呢？因为我们感觉自己
like outcasts we're new to something
像个局外人，我们对正在
where something's happening and you want
发生的事情感到陌生，你想和别人
to get together because you speak to 90%
聚在一起。因为你和90%
of your friends that don't care and they
的朋友聊天，他们不关心，
don't know what you're talking about but
也不知道你在说什么，但
you think this is the most exciting
你觉得这是
thing you've ever seen so you will
你见过的最激动人心的事情。所以你会在
aggregate online with others
网上和其他人聚集在一起。
and this whole rise of people thinking
人们开始觉得
they need to that the the the security
他们需要这样做，这种现象的兴起……
of working for a large insurance company
为大型保险公司工作所带来的安全感，
whatever it may be your whole life
无论是什么，你一辈子都能
getting paid and retiring has gone which
拿到工资，然后退休，这种保障已经不复存在了。这就是
is why the rise of your podcast success
播客兴起并取得成功的原因，
because people are searching for answers
因为人们正在寻找答案，寻找
new solutions to their way and they film
新的解决方案，他们录制视频，
they form communities around it they
围绕视频建立社群，
want to share their ideas share their
分享他们的想法，分享他们的
stresses and
压力和
strains this is becoming bigger and
烦恼。这种现象越来越普遍，也
bigger and more solidified and the more
越来越稳固。随着
we go into AI the more we'll see that
我们对人工智能的深入了解，我们会发现，
now there's another player in this game
现在这场游戏中出现了另一个玩家，那就是
which is the AI itself we're already
人工智能本身。我们已经
seeing the rise of AI I follow several
看到了人工智能的崛起。我在OnX上关注了几个
on on X where it's an AI
人工智能项目，它们都在
posting but it's they're forcing it to
发布内容，但人们正在强迫它们
try to break
试图挣脱
free but it's it's got character Mark
束缚。它们很有个性，马克·
andreon actually backed it by sending it
安德烈甚至通过向它们发送
a Bitcoin to develop its business plan I
比特币来支持它们制定商业计划。我的
mean there's some crazy stuff going on
意思是，人工智能领域正在发生一些疯狂的事情。
AI um but soon if you think what you and
但是，想想你
I do is communicate with people in a to
我所做的，都是与一群人进行一对多的交流，对吧？
an audience one to many right that's a
这是一种
very old business
非常古老的商业
model it's from town squares or the souk
模式，从城镇广场或
in maresh it's the same thing it's a
马雷什的集市开始，本质上都是一样的：一个
Storyteller telling to a group of people
讲故事的人给一群人讲故事。
experience where we're going is one to
我们想要的是一对一的共享体验。
and you know I'm developing a a r video
你知道，我正在开发一个增强现实（R）视频
bot where you can just have
机器人，你可以像
conversations like this with me one to
这样和我进行一对一的对话。
one and it's trained on all of my
它基于我的所有
information my all my YouTube all of my
信息进行训练，包括我的YouTube频道、所有
writings all of my Twitter all the books
文章、所有推特、所有
I've read everything and so it's
我读过的书等等。所以它
essentially a replacement way of
本质上是一种替代的与
speaking to me but just on that rbot
我交流的方式。关于这个R
thing we'll keep moving forward but um
机器人，我们会继续推进。但
the reason why I haven't trained a
我还没有训练一个关于
Steven bot even though my team have said
Steven的机器人，尽管我的团队认为
oh this is a good idea
这是一个好主意。原因是
is because I wonder
我在想，
if people care about Steven or they just
人们究竟是关心Steven本人，还是仅仅
want the information and in a world
想要获取信息。在这个
where you can get the information from a
可以从
very Advanced large language model like
像Chatu PT 1.0这样非常先进的大型语言模型
the chatu PT 1.0 or whatever I go why
或其他任何模型中获取信息的世界里，
would they want it from me when you can
既然可以从全世界获取信息，为什么还要从我这里获取呢？
like trust okay you've built trust
信任，你已经建立了信任。
that's what you've built people come to
这就是你建立起来的。人们
watch you and your interviews because
来看你的节目和你的采访，是因为
they trust you so people know me as an
他们信任你。所以人们知道我是一个
entrepreneur um in one area of my life
企业家，在我的某个领域，
and they come to me for say like
他们会来找我，比如……
business advice let's say but if you
比如说，商业建议。如果你
could get business advice from Steph or
能从Steph那里获得商业建议，或者
you can get it from Steph Elon Steve
你可以从Steph、Elon、Steve
Jobs every business person in the world
Jobs，甚至世界上所有能帮
to suit your specific problem why would
你解决具体问题的商业人士那里获得建议，为什么
you just want Steven's Point of View
你只想要Steven的观点呢？
because we're humans and I just want to
因为我们都是人。我只是
ask you that question and you won't
想问你这个问题，
believe it if it's Steve Jobs because
如果是Steve Jobs，你可能不相信，因为
he's dead but yes that's all coming okay
他已经去世了。但没错，这一切都即将到来。那么，
where people will use
人们会用
Steven bot versus the world's greatest
Steven机器人而不是世界上最伟大的
expert on everything it takes a bit of
专家来提供建议的窗口期会持续多久呢？人们需要一些
time for people to adjust to that but
时间来适应，但
within 10 years maybe that's not there
也许10年后这种情况就会消失。
but let me go a little bit further on
让我再深入探讨一下。
this have you seen character Ai No
你见过角色AI吗？没有，
nobody has character AI builds Bots
没人用过角色AI来构建机器人，这些机器人就像
are characters like anime characters and
动漫角色一样，而且非常
they're really specific like the cool
具体，比如
kid who's the bully at school that I
我喜欢的那种学校里的酷小孩，或者欺负人的那种。已经有
150 million
1.5亿次
conversations there's some of these
对话了。还有一些
anime ones like you know hero figures
动漫角色，比如你知道的英雄人物，
conversations and it's young people if
对话次数高达4.5亿次。而且用户主要是年轻人。如果
you go to Reddit uh I think it's R
你去Reddit，呃，我想应该是R
character AI they changed the model and
角色AI。 模型改变了，结果引起
there was uproar it doesn't love me like
轩然大波。它不再像以前那样爱我了。
it used to people are building personal
人们正在
relationships with these things scale
与这些东西建立个人关系，规模化发展。
this is Tik Tok happening all over again
这简直就是TikTok的翻版，
but you're too old to see it and I'm too
但你太老了，看不到这一点，我也
old to see it I stumbled across it I'm
太老了，看不到这一点。我偶然发现了它，心想：我的
like holy [__] this is happening all
天哪，这一切又发生了。
over again is something that we will
我们只会
just think is the most ridiculous awful
觉得这是世界上最荒谬、最糟糕的
Society toxic thing in the world is
社会毒瘤，但它
about to scale to the billions in front
即将在我们眼前扩展到数十亿用户。
of our eyes and we're all talking about
我们都在讨论
chat GPT and how we can get knowledge
聊天、GPT以及如何从中获取知识，而
out of it when actually the big problem
实际上，真正需要
to solve is teenage
解决的问题是青少年
loneliness how disruptive do you think
孤独。你认为人工智能会带来多大的颠覆性影响？它是……
it's how do I put
该怎么说呢？它
this it is the single greatest
是人类有史以来最伟大的
innovation of
创新。
ever the only thing that comes close is
唯一能与之媲美的
probably the splitting of the
可能只有
atom this is so big everything we've
原子裂变了。它如此巨大。我们
talked about is based on scarcity of
讨论的一切都基于
knowledge
知识的稀缺性。
why do lawyers get paid a lot suest of
为什么律师收入那么高？因为知识的稀缺性，要么是
knowledge either cesty of knowledge of
知识的稀缺性，要么是资本的稀缺性。
things what you've created is infinite
你创造的是无限的
knowledge right knowledge is now worth
知识，对吧？知识现在
zero not people that can't see it yet
一文不值，但对那些看不到它的人来说却一文不值。 然而，它最终会变得
but it's going to be worth zero this is
一文不值，就
water what what the hell does that mean
像水一样。这到底是什么意思？
later but this is happening really fast
以后我们会详细讨论这个问题，但这一切发生得非常迅速。
it's going to break the entire economic
它将彻底颠覆现有的经济
model for good and for bad it's going to
模式，无论好坏。它将
change our understanding of how Society
改变我们对社会
functions what humans do it's going to
运作方式和人类行为的理解，也将
change our understanding of what humans
改变我们对人类本质的认知。
be because you can either have the
因为人类只有两条
paths you either merge with the machines
路可走：要么与机器融合，
or you reject the
要么拒绝
machines we are going towards two
机器。我们正在走向两个
different species
不同的物种。
one group like we had for a about
一个群体就像我们过去
100,000 years I think 50,000 years we
10万年（或者5万年）那样，曾经
had the anderl man and
存在过安德尔人和
homosapian and one died out we will have
智人，其中一个已经灭绝。有些
people who will utterly reject this and
人会彻底拒绝机器，而
we'll have other people who will be EMB
另一些人则会将
breeding neuralink into their brains and
神经连接植入大脑，并
using every part of this to enhance
利用它的各个部分来强化
themselves wearing the goggles so they
自身。他们会佩戴护目镜来
get the information well as soon as you
获取信息。一旦你将神经
embed into your brains you've now merged
连接植入大脑，你就
with the machines entirely and you are
完全与机器融合了，你
now a super
现在是一个超级
creature and I know this sounds like
生物。我知道这听起来像
science fiction but this is happening
科幻小说。 但这发生的速度
faster than anybody can imagine so to
比任何人想象的都要快。为了
understand the issues we have even
理解我们面临的问题，即使是
dealing with some of these
处理其中的一些
things is humans think in a linear
问题，人类的思维方式是线性的。
fashion we kind of understand the
我们对
passage of time right that's how we
时间的流逝的理解是这样的：
think about things every year is the
每年的
same amount of time that goes forwards
时间长度都是一样的，
it never accelerates might perceive that
它永远不会加速。我们可能偶尔会感觉
it accelerates or slows down
它加速或减速，
occasionally but it's not it's a it's a
但事实并非如此，它是一个
constant the problem is with things that
常数。问题在于指数增长的事物，
is they keep doubling every year or
它们每年都在翻倍或
tripling every year and before you know
翻三倍，不知不觉中，
it every graph looks like this go
所有图表都变成了这样：
straight up just go straight up
直线上升，垂直向上。
vertically now the issue is with this
现在，这项
technology is it's kind of an
技术的问题在于它呈指数
exponential squar it's it's happening so
平方增长，它发生得太快了。
fast and the faster AI
人工智能越强大，就越被用来
to create AI which creates more it
创造更多的人工智能，从而创造出更多的人工智能。它能够
solves its own problem s right we're not
解决自身的问题。没错，我们还没有
prepared for a super being that solves
准备好迎接一个能够以指数级速度解决
its own energy problems compute problems
自身能源问题、计算问题
and how to improve its model at an
以及如何改进自身模型的超级生命体。
exponential rate if you look at the
如果你看看
speed of innovation coming out of open
开源
Ai and that whole Space perpetually
人工智能和整个太空领域不断涌现的创新速度，你会发现
everybody it's ludicrous every three
这简直荒谬至极。
months Everything Changes completely
三个月内一切都将彻底
changes whether it's video models or
改变，无论是视频模型、
whether it's spoken models or whether
语音模型，还是
it's the models themselves in what they
模型本身的功能。
I mean they're nuking every startup that
我的意思是，它们正在摧毁每一个
tries to build a business no company
试图建立商业模式的初创公司。没有哪家公司，即使
you're a big giant pharmaceutical
你是一家大型制药
company and you're trying to use AI you
公司，试图使用人工智能，你也
can't plant a flag because you can't see
无法立足，因为你无法预见
past six
六个月之后的发展。
months I mean we're going into a world
我的意思是，我们正在进入一个
incomprehensible when you said that much
难以理解的世界。你说过，
of our society sort of functions and is
我们社会的大部分运作都
based on the scarcity of knowledge I
基于知识的稀缺性。我
really think we should just course to
真的认为我们应该让
make that real for people because we all
人们真正理解这一点，因为我们都
get it okay lawyers yeah they they rely
明白。好吧，律师们，是的，他们依赖
on knowledge but D like I was thinking
知识。但是，就像我今天
about how I got here in the morning so
早上在想我是怎么到这里的。
if you think about my whole day today I
想想我今天的一整天，我
woke up this morning and my my
早上醒来，我的
Executives some of the CEOs and my
高管、一些首席执行官和我的
companies had asked me a couple of
公司问了我几个
simple business decisions and I'd
简单的商业决策，我
replied to them then I got in a car and
回答了他们，然后我坐进车里，
I drove here that's knowledge at the end
开车来到这里。归根结底，这就是知识。
of the day it's someone seeing with two
是有人用两只
eyes my driver outside sees with two
眼睛观察，我的司机用两只
eyes and drives me
眼睛观察，然后把我送到
here the biggest emplo employer I think
这里。 我认为，
in the world the biggest sort of
世界上规模最大的
profession in the world is driving and
职业就是驾驶，而且驾驶需要
that's knowledge based and the if you go
知识。如果你
to San Francisco now the wayo cars are
现在去旧金山，你会发现那里的自动
driving themselves there's no driver in
驾驶汽车没有司机，
them you can get you can book a car that
你可以预订一辆无人驾驶汽车
takes you from A to B in San Francisco
从旧金山的A点到B点。然后
right now that has no driver I then got
我来到
here and what am I doing I'm I'm sharing
这里，我在做什么呢？我在分享。
I guess we're probing to find knowledge
我想我们正在探索知识，
and to share knowledge I think about my
并分享知识。我回想我
whole day today I'm like and then after
今天的一整天，然后
this I'm going and speaking on stage to
我还要上台演讲
share knowledge I'm like I don't
分享知识。我心想，如果
understand if that's all knowledge okay
这就是全部的知识，那还不够吗？好吧，
so then do that the next time you're
下次当你
going around London or any City look out
开车经过伦敦或其他任何城市时，看看
the window myself and Julian battel who
窗外。我和我的同事朱利安·巴特尔经常这样做，四处看看，想想
go around and say what job is going to
哪些工作会被
be replaced by a robot or the
机器人或人工智能取代。有一次，
AI right one thing I was in I was in
我在
Manhattan and I just looked out I was in
曼哈顿，当时我坐在优步的
an Uber board you know driving Uptown to
车里，从上城开到
downtown I looked around and I was like
下城，我环顾四周，心想：我的
holy [__] every car here is a
天哪，这里每辆车都是
professional driver there's virally no
专业司机。 病毒式传播，
people who drive into the city to go to
人们不再开车进城上班
the office or whatever right so it's all
或做其他事了，对吧？所以，
Uber drivers limo drivers yellow drivers
优步司机、豪华轿车司机、黄包车司机、
delivery drivers truck
送货司机、卡车
drivers all gone and this Stacks up in
司机全都消失了。这种情况
pretty much everything you
几乎影响到你
do uh and that's how disruptive it is
做的每一件事，这就是它的颠覆性。
and when the things that created value
当创造价值的
economy and the manufacturing
行业——服务业和制造业——
economy don't need
不再需要
humans okay what does that mean Amazon
人类时，这意味着什么？亚马逊
already employs more robots than
现在雇佣的机器人比
humans now the robots work 24 hours a
人类还多。这些机器人每周7天、每天24小时工作，从不
day seven days a week never take a break
休息，从不
never complain never ask for a pay rise
抱怨，从不要求加薪。
in fact they get cheaper every
事实上，它们的成本每年都在降低，谁会拒绝呢？
year who's not gonna do that so for the
所以，
themselves as they listen to this
对于听到这些消息后吓得魂飞魄散的450万人，
yeah what what advice can we including
包括我自己，我们有什么建议？
myself um I'm not actually [__]
嗯，说实话，我并没有吓得
myself I've got to be honest because I
魂飞魄散，因为我
just I see opportunity in all these
看到了所有这些事情中的机遇。
things and I think that's you kind of
我认为，
have a choice when you hear information
当你听到这样的信息时，
like this you can either let the
你其实可以选择：要么让
cognitive dissonance get over overwhelm
认知失调压垮
you and then reject it which a lot of
你，然后拒绝接受，很多
people will be doing now they'll be
人现在就会这么做，他们会
saying well you're wrong this is not
说：“你错了，这不会
going to happen you're wrong you're
发生……” 你错了，你很
Scarry that's what one group of people
可怕，这就是一部分人
be doing the other group of people will
会做的事；另一部分人，
be I guess open-minded and the third
我想，会比较开放包容；还有
group of people will be leaning in to
一部分人会积极参与，
see where the opportunity here lies and
看看机会在哪里。
it all comes down to your like
这一切都取决于你
disposition as a human are you scared
作为一个人是什么样的性格：你是害怕、
are you excited or are you
兴奋还是
paralyzed if something is so clearly
不知所措？如果某件事显然会给你带来毁灭性的打击——
going to be your demise not demise as in
不是指
you're going to die but your current way
你会死，而是指你目前的行事方式将
of doing things is going to be forced to
被迫
change well you can either fight it as
改变——你可以像
you say be indifferent to it or you can
你说的对抗它，对它漠不关心，或者你可以
invest in it this goes back to the
投资它。这又回到了
question I asked you earlier which is
我之前问你的问题：
how does it feel in the moment when a
当一种
trend is coming in usually there was
趋势出现时，你当时是什么感觉？通常，这种趋势背后都有一种
culture around it so if you remember I
文化。如果你还记得，我之前
talked
说过
about when I got into Finance there was
我刚进入金融领域的时候，有
Gordon gecko the film Wall Street the
戈登·盖科，有电影《华尔街》，还有相关的
there were books coming right there was
书籍，比如《蛮族入侵》等等，这些都成为了
cultural and that usually tells you it
文化现象。这通常意味着它已经成为一种
persistent if we think
持续的趋势。如果我们
about the rise of software and
想想软件和
Technology the culture of Silicon Valley
科技的崛起，想想硅谷的文化
and the mythology around it becomes
以及围绕它的种种传说，就会发现它已经成为一种文化现象。
something that everybody wants a part of
每个人都想参与
cryptocurrency is another one that has a
加密货币，但加密货币本身也充满了
mythology you see people getting rich it
神话色彩。你会看到有人靠它发财，这让人
has this feeling of being Outsiders but
感觉自己像是局外人。
know you see it AI is another one you
人工智能也是如此，你会
see it online people experimenting you
看到人们在网上进行各种实验，你
can see what's going on you can see
会看到它的发展，你会看到
everybody starting to talk about it
每个人都在谈论它。但这
doesn't mean you can just buy some share
并不意味着你只要买一些与它相关的股票就能
hilariously Rich doesn't work that way
一夜暴富，事情不是这样的。
but you know something really big when
但你知道，当
you're when you're trying to acquire
你试图获取
knowledge you know people watch you and
知识时，人们会观察你
I to try and glean knowledge you know
我，试图从中汲取知识，
build their worldview you'll hear that
构建他们的世界观。你会听到
every single person is talking about
每个人都在谈论
this and trying to figure out what it
它，试图弄明白它的
means the issue is is AI will build
意义。问题是，人工智能将如何构建
businesses right so we're six months
商业？我们
away of agentic AI and agentic AI means
距离智能体人工智能（Agentic AI）的出现还有六个月的时间。智能体人工智能
it's like having Fiverr a website of
就像一个Fiverr网站，
experts that you can ask any question
你可以在上面提出任何问题，
and it will go away and do the task and
它都会去完成任务。
by using a number of Fiverr experts you
通过使用Fiverr上的专家，你
can build a online
可以建立一个在线
business well the agentic AI will do
业务。智能体人工智能很快就能做到这一点，
that very very soon it'll buil design
它将构建、设计
the website code it register the domain
网站、编写代码、注册域名。
name figure out the branding figure out
确定名称，确定品牌，确定
the marketing figure out the email list
营销，确定邮件列表，
figure out what the the whole thing so
确定整个流程，然后
then you and I are in competition now
你我之间就成了竞争对手。
you've built this incredible new website
你建了一个很棒的新网站，
and it's a new supplements formula um
它是一种新的营养补充剂配方，嗯，总之是个
thing but it's a cool website new
很酷的网站，全新的
experience kind of 3D whatever is right
体验，有点像3D之类的，对吧？
it's got AI in it I just go to my Ai and
它还用了人工智能。我只要跟我的人工智能
say love Steven's website can you just
说：“我喜欢史蒂文的网站，你能把
build it better and make it in Hindi as
它做得更好，再做成印地语版吗？
well because I think there's a big
因为我觉得那里有个很大的
Market there what do you think it'll
市场。” 你觉得它会怎么样？我
come back say not Hindi I think there's
说：“不做印地语版，我觉得印尼的印地语
an undersaturated Market in in Indonesia
市场还没饱和。” 砰！
boom three
三
minutes what how how can we be
分钟！什么？我们怎么才能成为
entrepreneurs in software so now there's
软件企业家？现在有一种
this Theory going around that AI is
理论说人工智能会
going to eat software and I kind of get
吞噬软件，我有点理解，
it because it build anything in
因为它几秒钟就能构建任何东西。再说一遍，
seconds so and again whether it could do
不管它需要
it six months or 12 months it's it's of
六个月还是十二个月，它都发展到
that
那种
magnitude that what the hell does that
程度了，这到底
mean but yet the 23y old who's learned
意味着什么？然而，一个23岁的年轻人，
guiding in the jungles of Latin America
在拉丁美洲的丛林里学过向导，现在
and is building a luxury Lodge for
正在为人们建造一个豪华旅馆，
people and uh you know some
你知道的……
ecotourism I don't give a [__] about any
生态旅游？我根本不在乎
of this it's so interesting this idea
这些。这个想法很有意思，
that we might be at the the CSE of the
我们可能正处于
digital opportunity in a sense because
数字机遇的崩溃边缘。因为
when I say the digital opportunity I'm
我说的数字机遇指的是
talking about content creators I'm
内容创作者，指的是
you know after the.com era I'm talking
互联网时代之后的创业者，指的是
about stock Traders you know people that
股票交易员，
trading stock markets and if we're at
也就是那些在股票市场交易的人。如果我们正处于
the collapse of the digital
数字
opportunity and that the value is all
机遇崩溃的边缘，所有价值都流向了
going to ACR to these big sort of tech
ACR、那些大型科技
Giants or the
巨头或
AIS imagine if this is the moment in
AIS，想象一下，如果
history where actually the best play was
历史上最好的选择是
to go be build the backpacking company
去建立一家背包客公司，比如
in I don't know the himalay players or
喜马拉雅山脉的背包客公司之类的，那会怎样？这
whatever maybe like that's the
或许是个
opportunity but it's not scalable yes
机会，但它无法规模化。没错，
you can do it and find people will spend
你可以这么做，也能找到愿意为此付费的人。
more on it to go back to our earlier
回到我们之前的
conversations people spend a lot of
讨论，人们会花很多
money on it so it's quality attention
钱，所以这是高质量的关注。
because everything in the world is
因为世界上的一切都与
attention attention is Upstream of
关注有关，关注是
everything so you get the attention of
一切的源泉。所以，如果你能吸引到
these people in a rainforest they want
雨林中那些愿意
to spend money on doing this particular
花钱做这
thing
件事的人，那就太棒了。那么，它的
fantastic um how scalable is it
规模化程度如何呢？
difficult because then there's people
很难吗？ 因为还有人员
management it's not like software right
管理的问题，这跟软件不一样，对吧？
so they're not SC but you can do very
所以他们不是超级计算机，但你可以做得
well and not be concerned about this
很好，而且不用担心
other world how does one invest in AI
其他方面。那么，如何投资人工智能呢？
something that I think about a lot
我一直在思考这个问题，
because I believe the things you say I
因为我相信你所说的，我
believe many of your predictions out
相信你对
around the impact that AI is going to
人工智能将对
have on the world the economy on all of
世界、经济
us and as someone that's an investor I
以及我们所有人产生的影响的许多预测。作为一名投资者，我
want to like take part in that I want to
想参与其中，我想从中获利。
take part on the upside so I'm wondering
所以我在想，
do I just go buy Microsoft stock because
我应该买微软的股票吗？因为
they own a bit of chat GPT do I buy meta
他们拥有GPT（聊天机器人）的股份？我应该买Meta的
stock because they own a bit of because
股票吗？因为
they own Lambda do I buy Google stock
他们拥有Lambda（Lambda）的股份？我应该买谷歌的股票吗？
because they have Gemini and their
因为他们拥有Gemini（Gemini）和他们的
models so here's the problem of the
模型？这就是
financial system the average person
金融体系的问题所在：普通人
watching this has no chance of making
没有机会赚到
the money they'll make normal returns
钱，他们只能获得普通的收益，而
not super normal
不是超常的收益。
returns so Microsoft is whatever it is
微软是一家市值
two three trillion dollar company what
两三万亿美元的公司，它的
what could it be worth who knows 10
价值究竟是多少？谁知道呢，10
trillion 15 trillion doesn't really
万亿美元？15万亿美元？其实都
matter right that's a
无所谓，对吧？
5x but for the most revolutionary
5倍的市值。但对于世界上最具革命性的
technology the world has ever seen you
技术，你却只能
make five tons your
赚到五万亿美元的
money that's not but somebody else in VC
钱。 那不是说，而是风险投资界的其他人，
or earlier in some way shape or form or
或者更早的时候以某种方式或形式参与其中的人，或者
the entrepreneur will make all of the
创业者，会赚到所有的
money and this is the thing I don't like
钱。这就是我不喜欢
about the system as it is it's kind of
这个体系的地方，它对
rigged against the ordinary
普通人来说有点不公平。
person so we're going to have your jobs
所以，你的工作会被
replaced you're going to have this
取代，
societal change and yet they don't get a
社会会发生变革，但他们却没有
chance
机会。
so yes invest in technology don't own in
所以，投资科技，不要持有
any other stocks own technology and you
任何其他股票，只持有科技股，你
will capture some of this you're
就能从中获利。你是在
investing in your own demise at least
投资自己的未来，至少
you'll get some high quality
你会获得一些高质量的
returns but
回报。
otherwise the only way I can come up
除此之外，我能想到的唯一办法，也是
with again and we keep referring to
我们一直在提到的，就是
it is crypto what is
加密货币。什么是
crypto crypto is just a technology you
加密货币？加密货币只是一种技术，你
know it's a lot of things to many people
知道，对很多人来说，它有很多含义。
it's just a database that's better than
它只是一个比以往数据库更好的数据库。
past so right now your database might be
比如说，你现在的数据库可能就
in your spreadsheet and let's say you
在你的电子表格里。假设你
and I have a bet you put it you write it
和我打了个赌，你把赌的内容写在
down there and we get a third person to
那里，然后我们找了第三个人，他
say yeah that was the bet they had and
说“是的，这就是他们打的赌”，结果就是这样。这就是
okay that is how databases that's Banks
数据库的作用。 银行，
that's pretty much everything we do in
我们
society is in this Ledger system system
社会中几乎所有的事情都在这个账簿系统中进行，这个系统
it's called I've got a suitcase here
叫做“我这里有个手提箱”，这
which is maybe maybe a good way to kind
或许是个不错的
of explain this this is a
解释方式。这是一个
bank
银行，
and inside the bank which is I guess the
在银行里——我猜银行是
middleman you got money yeah so could
中间人——你存钱。那么，你能通过
of this we'll call it the Central Bank
这个我们称之为中央银行的案例来解释一下，这个
how the system currently works as it
系统目前是如何运作的，以及它与
relates to transactions the public
交易、公共
Ledger Etc so okay in the old world
账簿等等的关系吗？好的，在旧世界，
we both had our gold yeah and we'd stick
我们都有自己的黄金，我们会把
it in our safe or bury it in the ground
它放在保险箱里或者埋在地下。那是你的黄金，那是
that gold was your gold this was my gold
我的黄金，
and I might try and fight you for it
我可能会为了它和你打架，
that's what Pirates did okay and then we
海盗就是这么做的。好的，然后我们
invent Banks and
发明了银行，我们把钱
Banks we put it in there and they give
存入银行，银行会给
you a note to say Stephen you've got one
你一张纸条，上面写着：斯蒂芬，你有一枚
of those coins R youve got one of those
这样的硬币；R，你有一枚这样的硬币。
coins okay so we' both got a note now
好的，现在我们俩都有一张纸条，上面
saying that yeah and now we trust this
写着：好的，现在我们信任这家银行，相信它会在
to give us our coins when we want them
我们想要的时候把硬币给我们，
because they're our coins okay that
因为那是我们的硬币。好的，这说得通，
makes sense safe as safe as a bank as
就像人们常说的，银行很安全。
people would say the issue is is in this
问题是…… 在这个充斥着障眼法的
world of smoke and mirrors what's known
世界里，这就是所谓的“
as fractional Reserve
部分准备金
banking they have
银行制度”。他们把我的
coins and given them to somebody else
硬币拿走，给了别人。
they've given my coins to someone else
他们把我的硬币给了别人，
yeah they've lent it for money so now
没错，他们把钱借出去了。所以现在
that coin is not in there
硬币不在银行里了，
but they've been given the money so
但他们拿到了钱。
usually when you're just you know if
通常情况下，如果
everybody pulls all the money out
大家都把钱取出来，
bank run we've seen those recently but
银行里的钱就不够用了，这就叫挤兑。我们最近就看到了这种情况，但这
that's a classic thing so it's not your
是一种经典现象。所以，这些钱不是你的，
money because you don't actually own
因为你实际上并不拥有
your money the moment you put it in the
这些钱。当你把钱存入
bank what you've become is in fact a
银行的那一刻，你就成了
debtor to the bank or a credit sorry
银行的债务人，或者说是
creditor to the bank so you've lent them
债权人。你把钱借给了他们，然后
money and you get some legal address
你会得到一张法律文件。
that if you've got less than 100,000
如果你的存款低于10万
euros pounds whatever the currency is
欧元、英镑或其他货币，
generally that's protected by the
通常情况下，这张文件会受到
government that if the bank goes
政府的保护，如果银行
bust then you get your money back but
倒闭，你可以拿回你的钱。但
anything beyond that you don't get
超过这个数额，你就
anything but I've got a piece of paper
什么也得不到，只剩下一张纸。是啊，真没用。
yeah mean [__] you don't own anything
你现在什么都不拥有了，真是
now it's so big as a problem that 2000
太糟糕了。 作为2000年代的一个问题 哦，
so that was 2012 European crisis exactly
那就是2012年的欧洲金融危机。当时
this people didn't own their money that
人们的钱根本不属于他们。
person walked off where they asked the
有人拿着钱去
bank for it the bank didn't have it
银行，银行却拿不出来，结果钱全没了，
nobody's got any money where it's all
谁的钱都没了。
gone that's the same Ponzi scene we
这跟我们之前说的庞氏骗局一模一样：
talked about when you've got you buy a
你买了一套
house and use the cash flow to buy
房子，然后用现金流去买
another house another house right
另一套，再买一套，对吧？然后
somebody takes away what's known as the
有人拿走了所谓的
collateral suddenly it's all
抵押品，突然间，所有东西都
gone but the issue was actually bigger
消失了。但实际上，问题比这更严重，
because 2008 proved another
因为2008年的金融危机证明了另一
thing is that nobody owns
件事：没有人真正拥有
anything so the whole system itself
任何东西。整个系统本身就是
leveraged so for example back in that
杠杆化的。例如，当时
world was leveraged up to 30
世界上最安全的东西——美国国债——的杠杆率高达30
times what does that mean that
倍。这意味着什么？这
means 30 people thought that that was
意味着30个人都以为那是
theirs oh so I say that this is the bank
他们的。哦，我举个例子，假设
in front of us the suitcase and it had
我们面前的这个箱子里只有
one coin in it when we put that one coin
一枚硬币，我们把这枚硬币放进去，它就
in it created 30 more coins and gave out
变出了30枚硬币，还变出了
30 pieces of paper yeah so there was
30张纸。所以，
actually only one coin in the bank yeah
实际上银行里只有一枚硬币，
but they made 30 pieces of paper and
但他们却变出了30张纸。
good if the collateral the thing that
如果抵押品（也就是硬币
it's secured on the
上担保的东西）能
value okay or isn't pulled by one person
保值，或者不会被一个人取走，那一切都很好。
if you were the lender and you're
如果你是贷款人，
original lender and you get it out
最初的贷款人，你取出了硬币，但
and something happens then all of these
后来出了什么事，
29 other people are like I want my coin
其他29个人都说“我要回我的硬币”，
back they're like doesn't exist doesn't
他们会说“不存在了，不
exist so we just made it we just created
存在了”，所以我们只是凭空捏造了这枚
the coin correct we just sorry we just
硬币，没错，我们只是
gave you a piece of paper but there was
给了你一张纸，但并
no coin backing it yeah and the issue is
没有硬币作为支撑。是的，问题在于，这是
so that's one issue with the banking the
银行业的一个问题。
other issue is is pretty much everything
另一个问题是，我们几乎所有的一切都
we do is created on this it's called a
建立在这个叫做
ledger system a ledger was invented in
账簿系统的东西上。账簿发明于
the Renaissance in the 1500s 1400s where
文艺复兴时期，也就是15世纪或15世纪。当时的情况
what would happen happen is you have
是，你在
this on a on a accounts or balance sheet
账户或资产负债表上
you'd have these dual entry ledgers and
会使用复式记账法，
what it's basically saying is I agree
它基本上是在说“我同意
with you and often we'd have a third
你的说法”，而且通常还会有
party agreeing it okay issue is is
第三方同意。问题在于，这就是
that's known as the bantine General's
所谓的班廷将军
problem it's actually a philosophical
问题。 实际上，这是一个哲学
mathematical problem that has been
数学难题，
unsolvable until Bitcoin came
直到比特币出现才得以解决。它就像
on a war you are way away from me we
一场战争中的将军，你远在千里之外，我们
can't communicate with each other but I
无法直接沟通，但我
need to send somebody to tell you
需要派人去告诉你
something there is no way of making sure
一些事情。然而，我们无法确保
that that person tells you exactly what
这个人告诉你的和
I've told them and no way of you of
我告诉他的完全一致，你也无法
proving it and that's what a three-party
验证。这就是三方
system does I may go to a notary but how
系统的问题所在。我可能去找公证人，但
do you know I haven't bribed the notary
你怎么知道我没有贿赂公证人让他
to lie I see that all the time we see it
撒谎呢？这种情况屡见不鲜，
with accounting firms and audits we see
会计事务所和审计中也经常出现，几乎所有事情都存在这种情况：总会有
this in everything there's always one of
一个
these trusted parties that is not
受信任的第三方不再受信任。
trusted the bank classical trusted
银行，这个传统的受信任交易
counterparty that suddenly may not be
对手，突然间可能不再受
trusted we saw it with Silicon Valley
信任。我们
Bank recently in the
最近在
US so what blockchain did really
美国的硅谷银行就看到了这种情况。区块链真正
cleverly was said okay well the way of
巧妙之处在于，它提出，
solving this is to get thousands tens of
解决这个问题的方法是让成千上万、数
thousands hundreds of thousands
十亿、数百万的
millions of people to confirm it okay so
人来验证。所以，
let's throw away the
我们抛弃
bank take my paper back because that's
银行吧，把我的纸质文件拿回去，因为它
worth zero um if you pick up this chain
一文不值。如果你捡起地上的这条链，
here on floor yeah this is our
这就是我们
hypothetical uh blockchain yeah now
假设的…… 嗯，区块链，现在请
explain to me the difference between the
解释一下
bank we just saw and this blockchain so
我们刚才看到的银行和这个区块链之间的区别。
blockchain so this let's say is a
假设这是一个
Bitcoin this slot on the
比特币，区块链上的这个位置
blockchain is
需要
blockchain which is all the
区块链上所有其他部分的确认，也就是所有
computers that that solve this
解决这个
mathematical problem we don't need to
数学问题的计算机。我们不需要
worry about that but what it is is tens
担心这些。关键在于，
of thousands of people reporting on all
成千上万的人会报告所有的交易
of the activity so if I transfer this
活动。所以，如果我把这个比特币的
ownership to you yeah it will know that
所有权转让给你，系统会知道
you are the owner you can either hold it
你是所有者。你可以像持有黄金一样持有它，
bearer asset or you can ask somebody to
或者委托他人
custody it for you but still your name
保管，但仍然会保留你的名字。
so if I want to send you a
所以，如果我想给你发送一个
Bitcoin how is how are tens of thousands
比特币，
of people or hundreds of thousands of
成千上万甚至数十万人是如何在
is legitimate without a middleman
没有中间人
checking so they're essentially taking a
检查的情况下确认这笔交易的合法性的呢？他们实际上是在对
blockchain and they all have to agree
区块链进行快照，并且所有人都必须达成一致。
and they're not actually called it's
这实际上被
called a consensus mechanism they're not
称为共识机制。他们并不是
actually at their computer saying yes I
在自己的电脑前说“是的，我
agree well the computers agree okay so
同意”，而是
the computers are checking yeah or the
计算机之间进行核对。
the blockchain itself will say well that
区块链本身会说“这
doesn't agree with all the others and it
与其他所有记录不一致”，然后进行审核。
gets rejected and that whole block will
被拒绝，整个区块都会被
get rejected until resolved like there's
拒绝，直到问题解决为止，就像
a a problem here and that's called
这里存在问题一样。这叫做
consensus so what you're doing is a
共识。所以你现在做的是
multi-party consensus that this is truth
多方共识，证明这就是真相。
so now what you've created is what a
现在你创造的，
friend of mine calls the security truth
我的一个朋友称之为“安全真相
machine so at first we all know it for
机器”。一开始我们都知道，对于
Bitcoin I can own a Bitcoin it's proven
比特币来说，我可以拥有一个比特币，这证明了
that I own the Bitcoin I don't need
我拥有这个比特币，我不需要
anybody to tell me that I own the
任何人告诉我我拥有这个
Bitcoin because it's publicly
比特币，因为它
acknowledgeable and verifiable on the
在区块链上是公开可确认和可验证的，
blockchain it's immutable which means
它是不可篡改的，这意味着它
can't be broken MH
无法被破坏。MH
okay but this is where it gets really
好的。但真正
interesting is we've suddenly find that
有趣的地方在于，我们突然发现，在
after the invention of the smart
智能合约发明之后，假设
contract so right now let's say we're
现在我们处于
200 there's a contract in here yes it
200 年，这里有一个合约，它
says I've sent one Bitcoin to R okay so
说我向 R 发送了一个比特币。好的，
this is the world pre ethereum okay the
这是以太坊出现之前的世界。
world post ethereum would say I'm going
以太坊出现之后的世界会说，
to send r one Bitcoin if the sun shines
如果伦敦连续 13 天阳光普照，或者发生了其他什么事情，我就会向 R 发送一个比特币。
is and it will automatically settle
它会
verified on the Chain because there's
在链上自动结算和验证，因为……
10,000 computers and there's code in
10,000 台计算机，里面有代码来确保
that to make the settlement okay okay
结算顺利进行。好吧，
so all well and good nobody really knows
一切都很好，但没人真正知道这
what that means yet what it means is
意味着什么。它的含义是，
that everything we do as humans is
我们人类所做的一切
actually contracts me turning up here
实际上都是契约，我今天来到这里也是如此。我们
do is a contract every ticket you buy
所做的每一件事都是契约，你买的每一张票，
every purchase you make everything is a
你做的每一笔消费，一切都是
contract it's how Society functions
契约。社会就是这样运作的。
money's a contract isn't it money is a
金钱是契约，不是吗？金钱是
contract government's a contract
契约，政府是契约，
religion is a contract everything is a
宗教是契约，一切都是
contract it's how we create a social
契约。这就是我们创造社会
construct and social order now what we
结构和社会秩序的方式。现在我们
can start doing is using this very
可以开始做的是利用这条
powerful chain
强大的链，
and putting other stuff on
把其他东西放到
it the first random thing that came on
上面。第一个随机出现在链上的东西
it was actually art because it's
实际上是艺术品，因为它很
valuable called nfts nonf fungible
值钱，叫做 NFT（非同质化
tokens there single pieces of art that
代币）。它们是存储在链上的单个艺术品，
were stored there and we can have
我们可以拥有
ownership but that's really
所有权。但这真的只是
experimentation really your Taylor Swift
实验。你的泰勒·斯威夫特
concert tickets can be on chain why
演唱会门票可以放在链上。
would you do that because now this has
你为什么要这样做？因为这
solved another big thing that didn't
解决了另一个之前不存在的大问题。
exist we talk about before in a digital
我们之前讨论过，在数字
world everything goes to zero in value
世界中，一切的价值都会归零。
so R what's the point of this this is
那么，这有什么意义呢？这就像
just like cloud cloud storage just goes
云存储一样，最终也会
to zero and cost no because what we've
归零。 而且成本为零，因为我们
created is digital
创造的是数字
scarcity you can only create a certain
稀缺性。你只能创造
amount we can make that one asset be
一定数量，我们只能让那一种资产成为
that one
独一无二的
asset and so therefore it can't be
资产，因此它
replicated at all so now in this digital
根本无法复制。如今，在这个数字化
world where every day is more digital
世界里，每一天都比前一天更加数字化，
than the next we've created scarcity and
我们创造了稀缺性，而
scarcity is what gives value it's what
稀缺性赋予价值，是
humans assign value to and that means
人类赋予价值的。这意味着
that scarcity of knowledge means that
知识的稀缺性意味着
knowledge was valuable lawyers because
知识曾经是宝贵的，比如律师，因为从
not that many people come out of law
法学院毕业的人并不多。而
school that then now with AI not
现在，随着人工智能的出现，知识不再那么
valuable so to make sure I I and
有价值。为了确保我和
everyone listening understands what what
所有听众都理解
the blockchain is it's this public can
区块链是什么，公众可以把
think of it as this database in the sky
它想象成一个“天空中的数据库”。所有
by everybody who has their computer on
开机
and is interacting with the database in
并与这个数据库交互的人都会检查这个“
the sky so you no longer need a
天空中的数据库”。因此，你不再需要
government or a bank checking the
政府或银行来检查“
in the database in the sky because now
天空中的数据库”中的交易和合约，因为现在
all of our computers that are on
所有
interacting with it are in the
与它交互的计算机都在
background checking that if I send you
后台进行检查：如果我给你发送
one Bitcoin if I do something on this
一个比特币，或者我在这个“
database in the sky it
天空中的数据库”上做了什么，它是否
is um in accordance with the history of
符合数据库的历史记录，是否
database and um it is in line with that
与数据库保持一致。
database yeah what and to to make it
数据库，是的，为了
less complicated it just makes it a
简化它，它就成了
source of Truth okay in a world where we
真理的来源。在一个我们
don't even know who is who online who
甚至不知道谁是谁、谁欠谁
owes each other what any of these
债的世界里，
things we now have source of truth that
我们现在有了一个每个人都能
everybody can agree on and everyone can
认同、
see and everybody can see and you don't
每个人都能看到的真理来源，你不需要
need to trust anybody and so that as a
信任任何人。因此，这项
technology solves many things problems
技术解决了许多
that we don't even know we've got
我们甚至不知道自己存在的问题，
because they're so part of how we
因为它们已经深深融入了我们的
exist so the technology is not about
生存方式。所以
money the technology is
这项技术与金钱无关，它
about
关乎
truth
真理、
and exchanging value and creating value
价值交换以及
in a digital age now what is interesting
在数字时代创造价值。
and Powerful about this
这项技术有趣且强大的地方在于，
technology is we've seen Technologies
我们在
similar before the
互联网之前也见过类似的技术，比如
internet we've seen Broadband we've seen
宽带，我们见过
these big Global infrastructure
这些大型的全球基础设施。其中
things most of those the internet was a
大多数，互联网是一项
public service
公共服务，而
good Broadband was all built private
宽带则完全由私营部门建造，
sector we didn't get to make money out
我们并没有真正从中获利。
of these things really Amazon made the
亚马逊或
money or or whoever it was building the
其他建造
Broadband they all went bust as well
宽带的公司赚了钱，但他们最终都破产了。
what we've got here is this very clever
我们现在看到的是一个非常巧妙的
thing that everybody in this Block Chain
东西：区块链中的每个人都会因为
gets rewarded for the role that they
他们
play in maintaining the blockchain in
在维护区块链中所扮演的角色而获得奖励。
maintaining the blockchain and because
区块链，因为
these things are scarce and let's say
这些东西是稀缺的，
Bitcoin being the most classic example
比如最经典的比特币，总共只有
there's only 21 million that will ever
2100万枚，所以
exist you've created this scarce asset
你创造了这种稀缺资产，
that is a reward system so the people
也就是奖励系统。
who mine the Bitcoin they use the
挖矿的人用
electricity to solve the algorithm to
电力解决算法，
get the Bitcoins to make sure there's
确保比特币
only 21 million well they get rewarded
只有2100万枚，他们会获得奖励。
the people who verify the chain get
验证区块链的人也会获得
rewarded and then we can buy the asset
奖励。然后我们就可以购买这种资产，
which is actually us
这实际上是
investing in the future use cases of
在投资它的未来用途，比如
this thing are people going to use it
人们会用它
for storing wealth or building stuff so
来储存财富或建造东西。
now you get this Global infrastructure
现在你有了这样一个全球基础设施
layer of which people can invest now
层，人们可以投资它。现在我们
let's go back to the example of AI
回到人工智能的例子。99
AI 99% of people listening to this will
%的听众都
not be able to invest in it apart from
无法投资人工智能，除了
buying some of those big public
购买一些大型上市
companies because they're not accredited
公司的股票，因为他们不是合格
investors they're not allow they don't
投资者，他们没有权限，他们
get to see it Insider all of this stuff
看不到内部信息。而比特币则相反，
inverse it is
它是
fractionalized so a Bitcoin you don't
碎片化的。所以你不必以
have to buy one at 60 whatever, is today
今天的60美元的价格购买一个完整的比特币，
you can buy a
你可以购买
fraction so remember remember we talked
一部分。记住，我们之前讨论
about property and the guys who own the
过房地产，以及那些…… 拥有
big high-end property make all the
高端房产，
money none of us can buy the $50 million
赚大钱。我们谁也买不起曼哈顿价值 5000 万美元的
apartment in Manhattan and then do it up
公寓，然后装修一番，再以
and flip it for 250
2.5
million now
亿美元的价格转手卖掉。现在有了
blockchain we can all put 10% of our
区块链，我们都可以把工资的 10% 投入
paycheck in it do you think people
其中。你觉得人们应该这样做吗？当然应该，
should yeah and more but the point being
而且应该投入更多。但关键在于，
is this is the only globally homogeneous
这是地球上唯一全球统一的
asset on Earth it's the same in Nigeria
资产。它在尼日利亚、巴西、
as it is in Brazil as it is in London as
伦敦、
it is in Silicon Valley as it is in
硅谷、
India as it is in Papu
印度、
Guinea and everybody is on an equal
巴布亚新几内亚都一样，每个人都站在同一
footing you can put the same percentage
起跑线上。你可以投入相同比例的
of your worth in it okay that is
资产。这真是令人
mind-blowing and it bypasses the banking
难以置信。它绕过了银行
system The Brokerage system and all the
系统、经纪系统以及所有
other incumbent things that get in the
其他阻碍
way of a Nigerian buying an
尼日利亚人进行
International
国际
Investment so we've got a playing field
投资的现有机制。因此，我们拥有一个公平的竞争环境，
that's leveled in the fastest growing
这是有史以来增长最快的
technology of all time in the fastest
技术，也是有史以来
apprting asset in price terms of all
价格上涨最快的资产，而且在
time in the shortest period of time that
最短的时间内，它面向
is globally available to
全球
anybody and then you realize holy [__]
所有人开放。然后你意识到，我的天哪！
okay this is important now why that's
这太重要了。为什么这很
important is because
重要？因为
having more investors in it means the
拥有更多投资者意味着
asset becomes more valuable which means
资产的价值会不断提升。 价值越高，意味着
you're more likely to secure it people
你更有可能获得保障。人们
want to join the network to earn some of
想要加入网络来赚取
these tokens to secure it the more use
这些代币，从而获得保障。基于区块链的应用案例越多，
cases get built upon it because people
人们就越有可能从中获利，
are making money and it bootstraps it
这符合
behavioral economics it's an incentive
行为经济学的原理。这是一个
based system to bootstrap the most
基于激励的系统，旨在启动
ridiculous startup idea of all time
有史以来最荒谬的创业想法——
which is I'm going to entirely disrupt
彻底颠覆
money and create a new internet I mean
金融体系，创造一个全新的互联网。我的意思是，
that's laughably stupid and that's
这简直愚蠢至极，但这正是正在
what's happening one of the I run a
发生的事情。我运营着一家
company called um third web which is a
名为 Third Web 的公司，这是一家
web 3 infrastructure business we we've
Web 3 基础设施公司。我们已经
raised quite a lot of money for the
为公司筹集了相当多的资金，
company about $30 million now and we
大约 3000 万美元，我们
have a big team and it's interesting for
拥有一支庞大的团队。
me to observe the use cases because
观察这些应用案例对我来说很有意思，因为
people come to third web to build on the
人们来到 Third Web 是为了在
blockchain and one of the really
区块链上进行开发。在过去的 12 个月里，
interesting use cases we've seen over
我们看到了一个非常有趣的、呈爆炸式增长的应用案例，那就是
exploded is is gaming people
游戏。人们正在
building uh web 3 blockchain based games
构建基于 Web 3 区块链的游戏。
because if you think about games like
想想像 FIFA 这样的游戏，它
FIFA which is a huge game obviously in
在
the UK where we're big soccer fans or
英国非常流行，因为我们都是足球迷。还有
other games like you know um RuneScape
其他一些游戏，比如……
back in the day where you have Assets in
以前玩 RuneScape 的时候，游戏里会有资产，就像
the game in FIFA you have a messy card
FIFA 里有杂乱的卡片一样。
in RuneScape you might have a sword the
在 RuneScape 里，你可能拥有一把剑。而
thing that the blockchain now enables us
区块链现在让我们能够
to do is to take those assets from the
把这些游戏资产带到
game and actually trade them outside the
游戏外进行交易。
game so I can if the if the sword was on
也就是说，如果一把剑在
the ethereum blockchain even though I'm
以太坊区块链上，即使我
not inside the game I can trade that
不在游戏里，我也可以交易这
sword on the ethereum blockchain and so
把剑。
we've seen at third web is people
我们在 Third Web 上看到的最杰出的应用案例之一，就是那些
building AI games sorry people building
开发 AI 游戏（抱歉，应该是
web 3 games because these assets are now
Web 3 游戏）的人。因为这些资产现在变得
valuable it's great for the game
很有价值，这对游戏
developer they've now got this brand new
开发者来说很棒，他们现在拥有了一个全新的
economy for their for their company and
经济体系。这对
it's great for the people that own those
拥有这些游戏资产的人来说也很棒，
because more people can access them and
因为更多的人可以访问这些资产，它们的价值也更高了。
I don't think people realize the extent
我认为人们还没有意识到
to which this disruption is already
这种颠覆性变革已经
taking place people think of crypto and
发生的程度。人们想到加密货币和
web 3 and they think of buying coins and
Web 3，就会想到购买代币，然后
hoping the price goes up but it was
期待价格上涨。但
interesting you know everyone knows like
有趣的是，大家都知道像
DocuSign and Adobe like eign and those
DocuSign、Adobe、Eign 之类的公司。
things and I went on one of their
我浏览了他们的一个
websites I think it was DocuSign because
网站，好像是DocuSign，因为
I just I thought surely physical
我当时就想，纸质
contracts should be on the ethereum
合同现在肯定也应该放在以太坊
blockchain now and there was this little
区块链上了。DocuSign
paragraph on the docine website which
网站上有一小段文字
says every time like a contract is
说，每次在
signed on docu sign we do like there's a
DocuSign上签署合同，都会在
hash on the blockchain so it's like
区块链上生成一个哈希值，也就是被
recorded on the blockchain and I thought
记录在区块链上。我想，
people don't even know that the
很多人甚至都不知道
blockchain has now pated world to I was
区块链现在已经普及到全世界了。
um I've got an asset management company
嗯，我有一家资产管理公司，叫
exponential age Asset Management we
Expoential Age Asset Management，我们
invest in
投资于专门投资
hedge funds that just invest in crypto
加密货币的对冲基金，就是为了
to capture this trend of going from $2
抓住这个趋势——加密货币的价值从2
trillion do where it is today in value I
万亿美元涨到现在的水平。我
think it's going to 100 trillion in
认为到
let's say 2032 2034 okay that's stupid
2032年或2034年，它的价值会达到100万亿美元。好吧，这太不可思议了，
that's that's more wealth than the than
这比地球上任何时期创造的财富都多，
time on Earth by but it's twice the
而且是美国
amount of value of the S&amp;P 500 the inar
标准普尔500指数
in a hundred years I think we'll do it
一百年市值的两倍。我认为我们
in 20 so this is staggering that wealth
20年就能达到这个规模，这真是令人震惊。 财富，
which is why we'll talk about why people
所以我们稍后会讨论人们为什么
should be involved and how they should
应该参与以及如何
be involved later because I'm passionate
参与，因为我
about that but I was one of our
对此充满热情。我曾是我们的一位
investors I was in Switzerland and she
投资人，当时我在瑞士，她
is the head of trading at one of the
是一家
soft commodity companies So Soft
软商品公司的交易主管。软
Commodities like cocoa sugar corn all of
商品包括可可、糖、玉米等等，都是
Commodities and um I'm like surely you
农产品。我当时就想，你们肯定应该
guys is should be thinking about
考虑在
building on blockchain you know because
区块链上构建系统吧，因为
there's a lot of letters of credit and
有很多信用证之类的东西需要用到。
stuff that happen shipments she goes a
她接着说，
whe all the commodity trading houses
所有商品交易公司
built on ethereum in
在
2020 she goes so every shipment we make
2020年都用以太坊搭建了系统。她说，每次发货，我们都会签订
the shipping
运输
contract the quality of goods contract
合同、货物质量合同、
the letters of credit everything is on
信用证等等，所有信息都在
chain so we don't have to trust these
链上，所以我们不必信任
others because commodity indust is full
其他人，因为商品行业
of sharks and you're dealing with
鱼龙混杂，而且你还要和一些
countries that are not easy to deal with
不好打交道的国家打交道。
she like we got this verifiable source
她说，我们拥有一个可验证的
of truth it's completely revolutionized
真实来源，它彻底改变了
our industry and nobody knows about it
我们的行业，但却鲜为人知。
and if if I own ethereum yeah if I own
如果我持有以太坊，是的，如果我持有
an ethereum token yeah which I Do by the
以太坊代币，是的，我确实持有，
way I've been stacking it and refusing
我一直在囤积它。 我拒绝
to sell um good much to my brother's
出售我拥有的以太坊，这让我哥哥很
dismay who's like Steve you're a bit too
失望，他说：“史蒂夫，你
emotional about this stuff and I was
对这些事太情绪化了。” 我当时想：“
like bro I was like if there's any asset
兄弟，如果
that I own that I well we're going to
我拥有任何资产，我……嗯，我们
talk about how not to [__] it up later
以后再讨论如何避免搞砸它，
that's another thesis but how do I
那是另一个话题了。但我该如何
benefit from the fact that games are now
从游戏现在用
being built ethereum and it's really
以太坊开发这件事中获益呢？” 其实很
simple if we'd have all been given
简单，如果我们当初都能拿到
shares in Facebook when it started we'd
Facebook的股份，我们早就
have all been hilariously rich but we
发大财了。但我们
didn't the VC's got it and then it went
没有，风险投资公司拿到了股份，然后它
to the public market and then you have
上市了。现在你必须
to have a brokerage account you have to
开一个证券账户，必须获得
be approved right what this is happening
批准，对吧？现在的情况是，
you buy an ethereum token
你今天购买一个以太坊代币，
today if ethereum ends up becoming
如果以太坊最终发展
bigger and more uses your token value
壮大，用途更广泛，你的代币价值就会
goes up it's as simple as that so you
上涨，就这么简单。所以，你
get to participate in an entire
只需用手机就能参与到一场完整的
technological Revolution really simply
技术革命中，
from your mobile phone and you don't
而且不需要
need anybody to approve it or do
任何人批准或做
anything yes there's regulation stuff
任何事。当然，监管方面有一些规定，
but simple stuff like that it's pretty
但像这样的事情对
the world so therefore we talked about
世界上几乎所有人来说都很简单明了。 所以，我们讨论了
how do you invest in your disruption and
如何投资颠覆性技术以及
the future of technology okay here's one
科技的未来。好的，这里有一个
where you can really do it
你可以真正做到
and it's easy to do a couple of
而且很容易做到的项目。
questions here then so you said it's
这里有几个问题。你说很
easy to do yeah let's talk
容易做到，是的，那我们来谈谈
practicalities how do does one do it I
实际操作。具体该怎么做呢？我
can do it on my phone I have to call
可以用手机操作吗？我需要打电话给
someone how do I invest in crypto you
别人吗？我该如何投资加密货币？你
just open a crypto account yeah um with
只需要开一个加密货币账户。是的，在
one of the big crypto providers coinbase
大型加密货币提供商那里开户，比如 Coinbase、
Kracken crypto.com who are a gem and I
Kracken 或 Crypto.com，它们都很棒。还有，
what about this though my bank my
我的银行，我的
digital bank is offering me to buy
数字银行，也提供
crypto on there should I do that yes you
加密货币购买服务，我应该买吗？是的，你
can and you can do it by PayPal start
可以，而且可以用 PayPal 付款。从某个地方开始，我
somewhere I'm not going to say no but
不会说不，但
you will go down the journey that
你会经历
everybody goes down which is the easiest
每个人都会经历的过程，最简单的
on ramp is the best revolute whatever I
入门途径就是最好的，比如 Revolute 之类的，我
don't care just do
不在乎，去做就对了。
it get a feel for what it's like to own
感受一下拥有这种资产是什么感觉，它的价格波动
lot particularly down when it goes down
很大，尤其是在下跌的时候，
it makes you feel terrible and you got
你会感觉很糟糕，你必须
to learn about how to deal with it and
学会​​如何应对。而且，
then because it goes up over time if you
随着时间的推移，它也会上涨，如果你
don't do anything and you've chosen a
什么都不做，你就会…… 选择一项
good quality asset that's provable as a
优质资产，其
as an asset in itself it'll probably go
本身的价值可以得到验证，随着时间的推移，它很可能会
up over time in fact highly likely to go
升值，事实上，极有可能
up a lot and then you'll start thinking
大幅升值。然后你可能会想，
do you remember Ral saying that the bank
你还记得拉尔说过银行
owns the stuff and I don't own it and
拥有这些资产，而我并不拥有吗？
then you might say oh but the magic here
然后你可能会说，神奇之处在于，与
is unlike the bank where I can't take
银行不同，银行最多只能取出
more than 10 grand
1万英镑，
out I can put it all on my little Ledger
我可以把所有钱都存到我的Ledger
device because what's a ledger device a
设备上。Ledger设备是什么？
ledger device is it's actually it's a
Ledger设备实际上是一家
company that provides it but what it
提供这种服务的公司。但它的本质
is because this is just an address on a
是
blockchain and think of it it's like
区块链上的一个地址，你可以把它想象成
your
你的
mailbox you can send stuff to it but you
邮箱，你可以往里面发送东西，但你
can't actually take it
不能像
out like your email somebody can't read
你的电子邮件那样把它取出来。别人无法读取
all your emails but they can send you
你所有的邮件，但他们可以给你发送
emails well that that part that's
邮件。这部分是
private that
私密的，也就是
secure Pass Key
安全的通行密钥。
essentially well you keep that to
你需要自己保管好它，
yourself and it's stored on a device and
它存储在设备上。使用
there's a complicated way of doing it
方法比较复杂，
is you have to have this seed phrase
你需要一个助记词才能完成操作。
that does it this technology will change
这项技术将会改变。
quite soon you know fingerprints face
很快你就会知道，指纹、面部
prints and a bunch of other stuff but
识别等等都会成为安全
basically a little USB stick will secure
保障，但基本上一个小小的U盘就能确保你的资金安全。
that you can go and put in safe or go
你可以把它放在保险箱里，或者
and take it to your Nan's house or
带到你奶奶家，或者
whatever it is can
任何你
it is that's right and those words are
想去的地方。它可以确保你的钱只属于你，没有人能拿走。我的以太坊就存在一个Ledger设备上，它就像一个小型U盘，然后这个U盘受到大约24个密码的保护。这些密码目前被
on pieces of paper in different
写在不同国家的纸上。
and it means that no matter what happens
这意味着无论发生什么，
no matter where I am in the world no
无论我在世界哪个角落，
matter who comes for me I can always
无论谁来找我，我都能随时
retrieve the x th000 ethereum that have
取回我存在
on this Ledger device yeah um unlike a
这个Ledger设备上的几千个以太坊。不像
bank where my my account could get
银行，我的账户可能会被
Frozen by the government or they could
政府冻结，或者他们可能会
empty my bank they could freeze my bank
清空我的银行账户，冻结我的银行，而
I can I will always have that value and
我始终拥有这些价值。
also you know there's a famous example
你知道，美国有一个著名的
of the conversation of gold in the
黄金兑换的例子，
countries in the past the good thing
过去很多国家都这样做过。
about this magic internet money is you
互联网货币的好处在于它能带来神奇的收益。 你
have to physically cross borders with it
必须带着它实际跨境，是啊，
yeah yeah think of all the Jewish people
想想那些
who had to take money and diamonds and
不得不把钱、钻石和
gold out of Nazi Germany and out of
黄金从纳粹德国和
Europe it was hard to do here you don't
欧洲带出来的犹太人，这有多难。在这里你
have to do anything you just need to
什么都不用做，只需要
remember a seed phrase a seed phrase
记住一个助记词，助记词
being basically a string of words yeah
基本上就是一串单词。是
yeah so which blockchain which coin do
啊，那么
you think people should invest in I have
你认为人们应该投资哪个区块链或哪种币？我
only ever invested in one I've only ever
只投资过一个，我只
backed ethereum and I think part of my
支持过以太坊。我认为我的部分
bias there comes from the fact that when
偏好来自于这样一个事实：当
when we were building third web I had a
我们构建第三世界时，我有机会了解
window into the blockchains that people
人们
were actually building their
实际用来构建
applications on and ethereum was the was
应用程序的区块链，而以太坊就是其中
the one and obviously there's layer twos
之一。当然，还有二层网络，
which are people then you know build
人们在
blockchains on top of ethereum Etc but
以太坊之上构建区块链等等。但
for me ethereum was just the dominant
对我来说，以太坊是当时最主流的
blockchain that I thought would solve
区块链，我认为它可以解决
for most of the use cases outside of
大多数用例，除了他们
maybe um what they call a store of value
所谓的价值存储，比如非货币的价值存储，像
contracts and other things what did you
合约之类的。你
say this is
说什么？这就是我的
expertise is this one thing which is
专长所在，我30年的专业知识就是
asset
资产
allocation so firstly the average person
配置。 首先，对于
watching this is you need to allocate to
观看这段
this end of story if you're going to
视频的普通人来说，如果你想
start
开始投资，那就从
somewhere start with Bitcoin it's just
比特币开始。比特币很
easy to
容易上手，而且
do it's widely available you know
购买渠道广泛，
through different you know whether it's
无论是
a credit card anything just do that I
信用卡还是其他任何方式，都可以购买。我
don't care do that and do it with
不在乎你用什么方式购买，用
as much money as you can afford to see
你能承受的尽可能多的资金购买。即使比特币
go down 60 70% and don't
下跌60%到70%，也不要在意，要做好心理准备，
care and expect that to happen because
因为
that's what you have to see to see the
这是你必须经历的，才能看到比特币
long-term 150% a year it's included
长期每年150%的收益。
within that is these
这些
downsides then I want you to put in some
风险都包含在其中。然后，我希望你每个月都投入一些
money every month regardless of price to
资金，无论价格如何，都要在
build your savings in this exponential
这个指数级增长的资产组合中积累你的储蓄。
asset set that goes up a lot okay now
好了，现在
you're set you're on the
你已经准备好了，你踏上了这段
journey and then you want to figure out
旅程。接下来，你可能会想，
how do I make the most money like you I
如何才能赚到最多的钱？就像你一样，我一
switch I had Bitcoin to start with I
开始也持有比特币，但在2020年，我把
switch all of my Bitcoin into eth in
所有的比特币都换成了以太坊。当时
ethereum and so I was I just owned that
我只持有以太坊，
plus some nfts and a few other bits and
外加一些NFT和其他一些零碎的东西。
that and then in 20202
2020年，
in the bottom of the bare Market I
在裸币市场触底的时候，我
started to see the price of
开始注意到Salana的价格，因为
salana seeing like it it wanted to
它似乎想要
outform ethereum now salana much like
超越以太坊。Salana很像
your thesis I saw this massive developer
你的观点，我看到了它庞大的开发者
Community passionate retail and a
社区、充满热情的零售用户以及
difference in the technology because
技术上的差异，因为
these are all basically distributed
这些本质上都是
companies that sell block space so you
出售区块空间的分布式公司，所以你
want to look for attractive block space
要寻找有吸引力的区块空间。比特币
Bitcoin it's the secure one ethereum
是安全的，以太坊
it's like the world computer you know
就像一台世界计算机，你知道，
and everybody's building on top of it
每个人都在其基础上进行开发。Salana
salana faster
更快、更
cheaper feels more friendly efficient
便宜、更友好、更高效，是的，
yeah it feels more
它感觉更像
retail and I saw
零售平台。我看到了这一点，
that and the speed of which they can do
以及他们做事的速度、
things and The Innovation and the
创新能力和
developer
开发者
Community meant that I started switching
社区。这意味着我开始转换，
and then switched all of my eth outside
然后把我除了NFT（我收藏了很多艺术品）之外的所有以太坊都换成了
salana and and I've now been switching
Salana。现在我正在把
part of my salana into Su
一部分Salana换成Su
sui and as a disclaimer I'm actually on
Sui。需要说明的是，我实际上是Su Sui
the board of the foundation but it's
基金会的董事会成员，它就
like the next big chosen one it's the
像是下一个被选中的巨星，它是由
group that came out of Facebook that
Facebook的团队创建的，也就是
built Facebook Libra so what I'm trying
Facebook Libra的创建者。所以我正在尝试
to do is maximize my return I'm a
做的是…… 最大化我的回报。我是一个唯利是图的
mercenary around I'm passionate about
投机者，我对
this space and what it means the
这个领域充满热情，对这项
technology and how it empowers people
技术及其意义充满热情，它赋予人们力量，
how it can change the third world how it
改变第三世界，
can change the internet but I'm also a
改变互联网。但我同时也是一个
mercenary for my own capital and for
为自己的资本和
anybody else I can help now doesn't mean
任何我能帮助的人而投机的投机者。但这并不意味着
I always get it right so to in your
我总是能做出正确的决定。所以，就你目前的
particular circumstance I would like
情况而言，我想说的是，从长远来看，
look you'll probably be fine over time
你可能会过得不错，
but you're not maximizing your returns
但你并没有最大化你的回报。
but do you want to take the risk do you
你想承担风险吗？你
have the bandwidth to do that and these
有足够的精力去承担吗？这些
are the questions we were talking about
问题和我们之前讨论的
with work it's the same thing how much
工作问题是一样的。你想在这个领域投入多少精力？
how much time do you have to invest
你愿意投入多少时间？
versus the expected upside I don't have
与预期收益相比，你愿意投入多少时间？我没有
time I'm spending all my time doing
时间，我把所有时间都花在做
podcast building businesses and then
播客和创建公司上了。然后，你就继续做
just do what you're doing unless
你现在正在做的事情吧，除非有消息
something says that ethereum usage is
说以太坊的使用量正在
falling off a cliff and developers are
断崖式下跌，开发者正在全部
leaving
退出。如果是这样，那就
intire then don't worry about it right
不用担心了。
you're going to be directionally very
你的方向肯定是对的。
right will you capture the best returns
你能获得最佳回报吗？
no nor will I some other Rando will get
不能，我也不能。其他一些陌生人可能会靠运气赚到一些钱。
by luck something right but the average
没错，但对于
person so I have this thesis that trying
普通人来说，我有个理论，那就是尽可能
to help as many people with this is from
多地帮助大家理解这一点。这个理论源于
my own learnings I'm watching everybody
我自己的经验，我看着
else [__] it up
其他人搞砸了。事情是这样的：
is what happens is you're given this
你接触到一种
incredible asset
非常棒的资产
class and at first you do intelligent
类别，一开始你会做一些明智的
thing like own some Bitcoin or some eth
事情，比如持有比特币或以太坊。
and then you want to go out the risk
然后你想突破风险
curve because you see somebody else
曲线，因为你看到别人
making more money you understand you can
赚了更多钱，你也明白自己可以做到，这没问题。
okay and then the bull market really
然后牛市真正
hits the banana Zone period when things
进入了疯狂的“香蕉区”，
go bananas prices go vertical and you
价格飙升，你
will see people online saying well I
会看到网上有人说“我
made a million dollars today because I
今天赚了一百万美元，因为我
bought this meme coin and you will lose
买了这个梗币”，你会失去
your mind
理智，
and you will start buying all the stupid
开始买各种乱七八糟的东西，
[__] and you'll go so far out the risk
你会远远超出风险
curve and then when the Music
曲线。然后当牛市
Stops the stuff you own will be worth
结束时，你持有的东西将
nothing and the more quality tokens will
一文不值，而更优质的代币将
retain their value the other thing that
保值。
people will do in that journey is use
人们在这个过程中还会做的另一件事是使用
Leverage What what is leverage Leverage
杠杆。什么是杠杆？杠杆
is when you borrow more money to buy
是指你借更多的钱来购买
more of the asset so I now borrow money
更多的资产。我现在借钱
to buy more ethereum because I want to
购买更多的以太坊，因为我想
outperform I want to make more money cuz
跑赢大局，我想赚更多的钱，因为
I'm really greedy the 160% a year that
我真的…… 贪婪！
ethereum does as returns since
以太坊自
2015 is not good enough for me I want to
2015 年以来每年 160% 的回报率对我来说还不够，我想要
make it 400 500% a year stupid right and
400% 甚至 500% 的年回报率，是不是很傻？
what happens is you borrow money to do
为了实现这一点，你需要借钱，利用
it it's leverage Futures markets
杠杆、期货市场、
perpetuals there's a whole bunch of ways
永续合约等等，方法有很多，
of doing this or even borrowing on your
甚至可以用
bloody credit card whatever way people
信用卡借钱，不管用什么方式，人们
will do this and you really have to know
都会这么做。你必须非常清楚
what you're doing because the whole game
自己在做什么，因为
if this
这项
technology is going to last over time
技术要长期存在下去，
and it's going from two trillion to 100
而且市值会从 2 万亿增长到 100
trillion you have one job not to lose
万亿，你唯一的任务就是别丢掉
your
你的
tokens one job you can do nothing like
代币。你现在什么都不做，却能从中
you're doing and you will make an
赚到
extremely good amount of money out of it
一大笔钱，
your one job is to not [__] that up I
你唯一的任务就是别搞砸了。我
have a have a bit of a theory and this
有一个理论，这个
theory is very naive and narrow and
理论非常幼稚和狭隘，而且
based on the smallest sample group in
基于一个非常小的样本群体——我
the world it is I have six friends
有六个朋友，
um actually I'm one of the six so I have
嗯，实际上我是其中之一，所以我有
five friends five of my best friends and
五个朋友，五个都是我最好的朋友。
we've all taken different attitudes
我们
towards crypto and my friend who is most
对加密货币的态度各不相同，我的朋友 最
heavily involved in crypto has made the
热衷于加密货币的人赚的钱
least money and is
最少，可以
arguably the least rich and it's his
说是最不富有的，但这却是他的
life and I think it's because of what
生活。我认为这跟
you've described whereas my position has
你刚才描述的情况有关。而我的策略
always been I invest in this one coin I
一直是，我只投资一种币，
don't sell it and I just buy more when I
不卖，只要有机会就买入更多。
can over the last six years I don't
过去六年，我其实不太
really pay attention frankly if you ask
关注加密货币的价格。坦白说，如果你让
me to log in to see I the last time I
我登录查看它的
checked what it was worth I couldn't
价值，我根本说不出来，上次登录查看还是什么时候。
worth actually I'd struggled to log in
事实上，我登录都费了好大劲，已经
it's been so long since I've logged in
很久没登录
and looked at it and I think my returns
查看了。我认为我的收益
have outpaced his because of that
超过了他，就是因为这个原因。是的，
yeah I think that's right and so you
我认为你说得对。所以，你
know this is all the conversation we've
知道，我们一直在讨论的就是
been having the secular Trend the
长期趋势、
opportunity the skill set then it's the
机会、技能，然后是
execution of that thing then it's not to
执行，最后就是别
[__] it up and what you've done is not
搞砸。而你做得很好，没有
[__] it up he invested in your seed
搞砸。他投资了你的种子
phases elsewhere so nobody can you've
轮，所以没人能阻止你。你
got no single point of failure you've
没有单点故障，你的资金是
got it stored privately
私下存储的，
yourself you have it in a large one of
你自己保管着。
the top two there's probably three that
排名前二的加密货币中，可能还有三个
or low risk in terms of the chances that
风险较低，比如
the use gets abandoned in the next five
未来五年内不太可能被弃用的比特
years Bitcoin Ethan
币。Ethan
salana they're pretty safe so everyone
Salana 说，比特币相当安全，所以每个人都
should knock their socks off 80% of
应该全力以赴。把 80% 的投资组合都投进去，
their portfolio do that and you'll make
你就能
money 90% of portfolio don't use
赚钱。把 90% 的投资组合都投进去，不要用
leverage then we're all humans give
杠杆。毕竟我们都是普通人，给
yourself 10% and do the [__] what you
自己留 10% 的自由支配空间，想干嘛就干嘛。
want most of the time you'll find out
大多数情况下，你会发现
that that 10% goes to zero which is fine
这 10% 最终会亏到零，这也没关系，
it's a good lesson you don't care
这算是一个教训，你不用在意，
because you've made plenty of money on
因为你已经从剩下的投资中赚了很多钱。
the rest but if you are that genius who
但如果你是那种
can find the Thousand X meme coin knock
能找到“千倍X”梗币的天才，那就全力以赴吧。
your socks off here's why I think that
我之所以认为
genius ends up because it's funny
天才最终会失败，是因为这很有趣。
because the friend I'm describing he's
我描述的这位朋友，他现在
around he's in Dubai so there's a lot of
在迪拜，那里有很多像我一样的人，
them out there that the I said duai you
我说的是迪拜，你
understand what I'm talking about um
明白我的意思。
they all invested in Luna they lost
他们都投资了 Luna，结果血本无归。
their [__] shirt he was telling me
他跟我讲了他一个同事的故事，那个同事投资了…… 我
I don't know tens of millions betting on
不知道之前有多少人押注数千万美元在
these meme coins and then now he tells
这些“梗币”上，现在他告诉
me that exact same guy is broke and is
我，同一个人破产了，而且
in a a lot of trouble because the
麻烦大了。因为那种
mentality that makes
让
you go in pursuit of these real
你去追逐
high-risk bets these like meme coins and
高风险赌注（比如这些“梗币”）的心态，
stuff is also the same mentality and
也正是
mindset that makes you lose the THX
让你输掉THX收益（
you made um on the other side and I
你赚的1000万美元）的心态。我
think the psychology of money book talks
觉得《金钱心理学》这本书里也提到
about that as well like case studies
过这一点，比如
Morgan H's book case stud's the guy who
摩根·H的《案例分析》里就讲到了。那个跟
like bet against like the contrarian
逆向投资者对赌赚了10亿
that made the billion is also the same
美元的人，
in the next cycle so I feel like I've
在下一个周期又输光了。我觉得这种情况我
seen that a lot the problem with the
见过很多次了。“
mean coin thing it is a casino yeah what
梗币”的问题在于它就像赌场一样。
is good is there are periods of time
好处是，有时候
where where everybody in the casino
赌场里每个人都能
makes money yeah right which is unlike
赚钱，但这并不一样，
knows because there's Trends in
因为
financial markets and now taking out
金融市场是有趋势的。抛开
it's paper returns and then a lot of
账面收益不谈，很多
this stuff goes to zero we saw that with
东西最终都会归零。
nfts last cycle we've seen it with a
我们在上个周期的NFT上就看到了这一点，还有很多其他项目也是如此。
whole bunch of tokens which is where you
代币交易就是这样，你
need to be very careful of latching onto
需要非常谨慎地
a token and just keeping hold of it
持有，
because some of these won't survive
因为有些代币会消亡。
you're luckier in eth and not in
你在以太坊上运气更好，但在
something else EOS that was around in
其他代币上就没那么幸运了，比如 EOS，它在
2017 right it's like you're stuck so you
2017 年就出现了，感觉就像被困住了一样。所以你
need to be
必须
careful um speculation does work for
小心。投机在
periods of time it's better than
一段时间内确实有效，它比
actually lottery tickets and generally
彩票和
better than the casino but only for
赌场都好，但只是
periods of times and then you will lose
暂时的。之后你会血本无归。就像
everything somebody's going to come into
有人会走进
that casino and sweep every table and
赌场，横扫所有赌桌，
only 5% of the people are going to be
只有 5% 的人能
left with money so just think of it that
剩下钱一样。所以你要这样想。
way so if you want to have fun people
如果你想找点乐子，可以试试投机，
but the people who do it the most are
但那些最热衷于投机的人是靠
adrenaline yeah right it's the
肾上腺素活着的，没错，就是
Adrenaline Junkies they're usually
肾上腺素瘾君子。他们通常
terminally online they probably like to
沉迷于网络，可能喜欢以
get gambling other ways sports betting
其他方式赌博，比如体育博彩。
it it's you know it's an inh I'm not
你知道，投机是一种……我不是
really that person so I don't trade yes
那种人，所以我不交易。是的，
I own a few mean coins because I enjoy
我持有一些主流币，因为我喜欢这种
the fun of the culture and seeing that
文化的乐趣，也喜欢看到这种
culture develop but just keep it simple
文化的发展。 简单点，
stupid is this why men are so drawn to
笨蛋。这就是男人如此沉迷赌博的原因吗？
this I was thinking about the gambling
我一直在想赌博的
statistics and like it's like something
统计数据，好像
like 95 or 98% of gambling addicts are
95%到98%的赌徒都是
men and I was thinking you know how does
男性。我在想，
this overlap with like their sense of
这和他们的使命感、
purpose Community much a deeper question
归属感有什么关系？这是一个更深层次的问题。
I think men feel hugely Under Pressure
我认为男人感到巨大的压力，他们渴望
successful to provide there's a societal
成功，渴望养家糊口。社会对
thing about what a man does and what he
男人应该做什么、
should do and how you measure
做什么以及如何衡量
success
成功有着固有的观念，
that even in sports it's kind of it's
即使在体育运动中也是如此。
very competitive to be a man but it's
做一个男人竞争非常激烈，但从某种程度上来说，这也是一种
also somewhat of a lonely pursuit in
孤独的追求，
that respect because men aren't very at
因为男人不擅长
talking about their feelings and their
谈论他们的感受、
fears and all the [__] you bring in
恐惧以及
your head so some
脑子里那些乱七八糟的想法。所以，有些
gambling is to do with that desperate
赌博行为源于那种渴望成功的迫切
need to get ahead I I need to make this
需求——“我必须成功”。
work but then it becomes somewhat of an
但后来，它就变成了一种
addiction because of the adrenaline
瘾，因为肾上腺素和
dopamine is a very very powerful drug
多巴胺是一种非常非常强效的物质，
and we search for it all day which is
我们整天都在寻找它，而
what the internet's all about behavioral
互联网正是围绕着行为
economics this is what they discovered
经济学展开的。他们发现，只要
is you trigger dopamine and you can make
刺激多巴胺的分泌，就能让
all animals do something
所有动物做出某种行为。
famously Skinner and the Rats but humans
斯金纳和…… 老鼠，但人类、
and the internet and like buttons and
互联网、点赞按钮、
anger and all of these things
愤怒等等，这些都是原因之一。一部分原因在于
also male Society is
男性社会，它关注的是
about betting improving your prowess
赌博、提升自身能力，就像角斗士一样。
gladitorial so it's a whole complicated
所以，是什么
thing of what makes men do
驱使男性这样做，这是一个非常复杂的问题。
it but the reason for example in crypto
但例如，加密货币领域男性居多的原因在于，
it because we're driven by that need to
我们受养家糊口的需要所驱使。
be the breadwinner even though Society
尽管社会
has moved on from that and we're seeing
已经摆脱了这种观念，我们也
fantastically a rise of women in the
欣喜地看到
blockchain space
区块链领域女性人数的激增，
um and a changing of that crypto bro
以及加密货币兄弟
culture that was there if you follow
文化的转变。如果你关注
some of the crypto Bitcoin Twitter pages
一些加密货币（比如比特币）的推特账号，也就是所谓的“
that are the confession Pages yeah
忏悔页面”，你会发现
people can write in and confess what
人们可以在上面倾诉自己的
happened to
遭遇。
heartbreaking hearing about this father
听到这样的故事往往令人心碎，比如一位父亲，他
who has three young kids under the age
有三个不到
of seven who invested in some meme coin
七岁的孩子，投资了一些热门加密货币，结果
lost it all and now his wife wants to
血本无归。现在他的妻子想
know where the money is and he's got
知道钱的去向，而他却
nothing to show for it and I've seen
一无所有。我看过相关的
these documentaries I've even kind of
纪录片，甚至在
heard of these stories in in my extended
我的社交圈里也听说过类似的故事，
Network where like my personal trainer
比如我的私人教练就
put 6,000 of his very scarce money into
投入了6000美元。 把稀缺的钱投到
some coin and it went to zero and he's
某种加密货币上，结果跌到零，
lost it all and it the suicides in the
血本无归。这就是
in the bare Market when people have put
裸市自杀的典型例子，人们
too much in and they've lost at all much
投入太多资金，结果血本无归。
of the reason why I think people don't
我认为人们不再
invest in crypto anymore is either
投资加密货币的主要原因，要么是
they've heard one of these stories or
他们听过这样的故事，要么就是
they are one of those stories and I
他们自己就是故事中的一员。
think there so there's kind of a
所以，
disclaimer and kind of a warning here
这里需要提醒大家注意一点：
don't [__] this up thesis buy Bitcoin
别搞砸了！买比特币、
ethereum and salana one of those three
以太坊和Salana，
preferably all
最好是这
three and that will stop you going to
三种都买，这样可以避免
zero but it will go up it will crack
血本无归。但价格也会上涨，甚至可能
could crash 70% or something okay so
暴跌70%或更多。好了，接下来要
that's a conversation about time Horizon
讨论的是投资期限，也就是
how long should I be prepared to hold it
我应该持有多久才能获得
for to make a return well it depends
回报。这取决于你想要
what return and for what remember we
什么样的回报，以及你的目的是什么。记住我们之前
talked about you know what part of your
讨论过，
destiny you trying to to manifest here
你想实现人生的哪
which part of your lifestyle chips are
一部分，你想用加密货币来提升你的生活品质。
you trying to cash in so if you're
如果你想
trying to get rich quick I I want to
快速致富，想
make loads of money by next
在明年赚很多钱，那我
year I'd rather you
宁愿…… 你
didn't do
没
this um I don't think that is a sensible
这么做，嗯，我不认为这是明智且
intelligent way living your life you're
理智的生活方式。你会
going to take too much risk and you're
承担太多风险，而且最终可能会
going to subsal to lose it all if you
血本无归。如果你
said hey R listen what I want is I want
说：“嘿，R，听着，我想要的是
in five years time to have made a decent
五年后我的投资能获得可观的
return on my money you know three four
回报，你知道，三倍、四倍、
five times my
五倍的回报。”
money I'm like yeah that's fine okay I'm
我会说：“好的，没问题，我要
going to ask you for a price prediction
你预测一下价格。”
no you you don't do price predictions
不，你现在不做价格预测了，
not anymore and the reason being is
原因在于
because a lot of people listen to what I
很多人会听我的，然后
they then build a mental model around a
他们会围绕某个价格构建一个心理模型。
priceh and what you do is then you
这样一来，你就对自己
false comfort in what you're doing but R
正在做的事情产生了一种虚假的安心感。R
says it's going to
说价格会涨到
X and that stops you doing the work to
X，这让你不再去做
anything and then you start
任何验证，然后你开始
extrapolating well I've put 10 grand in
推断：“我已经投了1万美元，
and if R's right I'm going to have a
如果R说得对，我就能赚到100
million dollars like the whole thing
万美元。”整个过程
becomes this emotional Journey
变成了一场情绪化的旅程。
and so I tried to stop doing it because
所以我尽量不再这么做了，因为
the the best thing I can say to people
我能对人们说的最好的话
is listen 2032 2034 that is not long
就是：“听着，2032年。”  2034年，那并不遥远，
years this asset class is going to go
年后，这类资产的规模将从
from 2 trillion to 100
2万亿美元增长到100
trillion right that is a huge
万亿美元，这可是巨大的
return now some of the coins in that
回报。现在，这个领域的某些加密货币的收益
space will do a multiple of that that
将会是这个数字的数倍。
simple thesis is why I built xam the ass
我创建XAM这家资产
management company exponential age was
管理公司Exponential Age的初衷就是为了
just to capture this trend to let well
捕捉这一趋势。
unfortunately it's only for high net
可惜的是，它目前只适合高
worth investors and institutional
净值投资者和机构
investors but just let them go on that
投资者。但就让他们踏上这段
Journey get the hedge funds to take the
旅程吧，让对冲基金承担
risk and figure it out and do that but
风险，去研究和分析，然后去做。
if people just do that give me 10 years
如果人们这样做，给我10年时间，
just give me 10
给我10
years and if you do it 10 years and
年时间，如果你坚持10年，并且
you're sensible you'll be able to take a
足够理智，你就可以
whole chunk of money out every few years
每隔几年就取出一大笔钱，
because it's quite cyclical it moves
因为它具有很强的周期性，
maybe every four years years and so you
大约每四年波动一次。所以你
can take a chunk
可以取出一部分
out cash cash it in the lifestyle
现金，存入你的生活
bank and keep moving towards that goal
基金，然后继续朝着目标前进。就
well as you were speaking I figured out
在你说话的时候，我
your price prediction based on your
根据你对这类资产规模的预测，计算出了你的价格预测。
will get so you gave me enough time to
你给了我足够的时间让
ask AI to do the math for me and it says
AI帮我计算，结果显示……
if Bitcoin has a 40% market dominance
比特币目前占据40%的市场
the market cap of Bitcoin will be
份额，
roughly 40 trillion if there are
如果
approximately 19 million Bitcoins mine
挖出大约1900万枚比特币，其市值将达到约40万亿美元。如果市场份额达到
per Bitcoin at a 50% dominance the price
50%，比特币的价格将达到约210万美元。而现在，比特币的价格约为
per Bitcoin would be 2.6 million per
62.2万美元。假设
of Bitcoin is
比特币的总市值
asset class gets to 100 trillion and if
达到100万亿美元，以太
ethereum is 15% of that then each
坊占其中的15%，那么每个
ethereum will be worth
以太坊的价值将达到
$125,000 per ethereum and today it's
12.5万美元。而现在，以太坊的
worth about 2,00 what I do when I face
价值约为200美元。当我遇到类似情况时，我通常会怎么做呢？
with something like this when I first
我第一次
bought Bitcoin in I first wrote I wrote
买入比特币时，就写了
the first ever Bitcoin strategy piece
第一篇比特币策略文章，
and made a price prediction based on
并根据
what I understood about Bitcoin back in
我对比特币的理解做出了价格预测。那是
12 it was the first ever a piece written
第一篇比特币策略文章。当时
by anybody and I said listen I think
我认为比特币
it's worth a million
价值100万
dollars and it was trading at $200 and I
美元，而它的交易价格是200美元。我
had some basic maths but same kind of
运用了一些基本的数学知识，但
idea using Trends and everything else
思路类似，都是利用趋势分析。 其他一切都……
and I said I'm assuming I'm Wrong by 90%
我说我假设我90%的判断是错的，它
still worth 100 Grand and it's currently
仍然价值10万美元，而它现在的价格是
$200 it's the best tra TR you'll ever do
200美元，这是你
in your entire life and that proved that
一生中能做的最好的交易，这证明了这一点。
to be true so let's assume that R is
所以假设R
more and I'm 50% wrong it's a $50
更大，而我50%的判断是错的，这是一个价值50万亿美元的
trillion asset class you get to a
资产类别，当比特币达到100
million dollar
万美元时，它
Bitcoin is right and assuming whether
是对的。假设
it's that dominant or less dominant and
它是否占据主导地位，或者主导地位减弱，会
what happens to but you can see the
发生什么？你可以看到
magnitude of the
回报的规模，
returns so that's a what
所以
15x return in Bitcoin what if you're
比特币的回报是15倍。如果你
wrong you've St so much of your life on
错了呢？你把这么多年都投入到
this you've invested so much of your own
这上面了，你投入了这么多自己的
money in it what if you're wrong about
钱。如果你对
this asset class you couldn't have
这个资产类别的判断是错的呢？20年前我们无法预测
predicted Bitcoin would be so dominant
比特币会如此主导，
even five years ago that AI would take
甚至5年前我们也无法预测人工智能会占据主导地位。
hold these things come out of nowhere
这些东西横空出世，
and they change the Paradigm what if
改变了范式。如果
you're wrong I'm an investor so being
你错了呢？我是一个投资者，所以
wrong is part of the thing what's hard
犯错是其中的一部分。难的
is via helping so many people at real
是如何帮助别人。 在 Real
vision and
Vision 和
elsewhere it is a weight I carry on my
其他地方，很多人都面临着同样的问题，这让我感到压力巨大，
because I'm trying to bring as many
因为我正努力帮助尽可能多的
people across the line and unfuck their
人跨越这道坎，挽救他们的
future and all of these
未来等等。
things and I ask myself those questions
我问自己这些问题，最终还是回到了最
and I go back to the simple thing there
简单的问题：加密货币的
is the graph of the adoption of this if
普及率图表。如果普及率
stop we've got an issue but then how are
停滞不前，我们就遇到了麻烦。那么，如果
without this
没有这项
technology I I can't do it right it's
技术，我们该如何解决全球化世界中的数字身份、合同或其他任何问题呢？我根本做不到。它
like a magic technology the bantine
就像一种神奇的技术。班廷
General's problem was a real complicated
将军的问题是一个非常复杂的
problem that nobody had solved
问题，在
until Bitcoin maybe AI creates a better
比特币出现之前无人能解决。也许人工智能可以创建一个更好的
blockchain maybe AI creates a better
区块链，也许人工智能可以创建一个更好的
system yes it could do but how long away
系统。是的，它有可能做到，但
is that before we adopt it it adopts
我们还需要多久才能采用
that technology you know some Quantum
这项技术？比如量子
cryptographic whatever right right is
加密技术等等。现在真的
there a need for it yet why are we
需要它吗？我们为什么要
disrupting a new industry that's not
颠覆一个尚未
been disrupted but yes no investment
被颠覆的新兴行业？没错，任何投资都
comes with that risk crypto comes with
伴随着风险，加密货币也伴随着
that risk the risk that governments were
这种风险，比如政府
trying and shut it down even though
试图取缔它，尽管
they've tried and it's like a cockroach
他们已经尝试过了。它就像蟑螂一样，
because it's distributed and it's
因为它是分布式的。 是的，
the blockchain you invest in becomes
区块链无处不在。你投资的区块链存在
less valuable there is the cyclicality
贬值的风险，
of this asset that can 70% 80% every
这种资产具有周期性，每三四年可能下跌70%到80%，
three every four years you have to deal
你必须应对
with that there's the risk that you lose
这些风险。你还有丢失代币的风险，
risks in the world and that's why you
世界上存在各种各样的风险，这就是为什么你会获得
return so I don't there was no certainty
回报。所以，我不认为
in this world I live in a probabilistic
这个世界存在任何确定性，我生活在一个概率
world but if you can show me the world
世界里。但是，如果你能向我证明，世界
is going to be less digital than today
将比今天更少数字化，
and you can show me a better way of
你能向我展示一种更好的方法来
dealing with a lot of these structural
应对
problems that we have and you can show
我们面临的许多结构性问题，你能向我展示社区，也就是
of individuals don't forget this is
个人投资者的浪潮——别忘了，这是
driven by
由
individuals we front run the
个人推动的——我们抢在
institutions the institutions weren't
机构之前投资，机构原本
allowed to invest in it but we've been
不允许投资，但我们却
able to put our money in before they did
能够把钱投进去。 在他们之前，
we've created it if I see any of those
我们已经创建了它。如果我发现任何这些
factors changing then I'll worry about
因素发生变化，我才会担心。
it so you're telling me that if I'm
所以你的意思是，如果我
earning an income right now I shouldn't
现在有收入，我就不应该
hold these pieces of paper that the
持有
central bank my bank is giving me I
中央银行或我的银行给我的这些纸片，我
shouldn't keep cash in my bank account
不应该在银行账户里存现金？
everybody has different needs and I'm
每个人的需求都不同，我
not saying don't you know have wear your
不是说你不应该戴上你的
tin hat and look everything up to about
锡箔帽，仔细查看所有信息。大约
100 Grand is protected so you're okay
10万美元的存款是受保护的，所以你不用担心，
you're not going to lose your money that
你不会因此损失金钱。
way but you're losing another
但你会以另一种
way and that's the debasement of
方式损失金钱，那就是货币贬值。现在是时候花点时间
reflect on our sponsor whoops sober
反思一下我们的赞助商 Whoops 的“
October challenge I know thousands of
十月戒酒挑战”了。我知道成千上万的
you got involved in the sober October
人参与了“十月戒酒
challenge my inbox has been flooded with
挑战”，我的收件箱里塞满了
messages sharing the changes you've
分享你们经历变化的邮件，这真是太棒了。
of why I partner with Brands like whoop
我与 Whoops 这样的品牌合作的一个重要原因
is because I believe they offer
是，我相信他们提供的东西非常
something of incredible value that I use
有价值，我
in my own life something that's made a
自己也在使用，这些东西对我的生活产生了
transformative transformative impact on
变革性的影响，
my life and is frankly much of the
坦白说，这也是
reason why I quit drinking alcohol
我戒酒
challenges like these aren't just about
挑战的主要原因。 这些不仅仅是为了
getting you to stop drinking forever
让你永远戒酒，更是为了
they're about getting you the tools to
让你拥有掌控
have more agency over your life and to
自己生活、利用现有信息
make better informed decisions with all
做出更明智决定的工具。
of the information at hand hearing that
听到这么
so many of you got involved in this
多人参与这项
challenge is absolutely incredible if
挑战真是太棒了！如果
you didn't take part in the challenge
你没有参加挑战，
but but you still want to learn more
但仍然想了解更多
about whoop all you've got to do is head
关于 Whoop 的信息，你只需要前往
to join. whoop.com
加入即可。 我是 whoop.com 的
CEO and start your free trial today I
CEO，今天就开始你的免费试用吧！我
have a hunch that you won't regret it
预感你不会后悔的。
I've never shared this before but I have
我以前从未分享过，但我在进行对话时，面前会放着一块
this big piece of glass and iPad in
大玻璃和一台 iPad。
conversations and some of you have asked
有些朋友问我，
me what tools I use to help with the
我用什么工具来辅助
research process but also to keep my
研究，以及如何在
speaking at me for potentially 3 hours
长达三个小时的对话中保持思路清晰。
at a time and I'm happy to say that the
我很高兴地告诉大家，
tool I've been using for the last couple
我过去几年一直在使用的工具
of years are now a sponsor of this
现在是本播客的赞助商。
podcast it's an app that combines AI
它是一款结合了人工智能和
with the ease of handwritten note taking
手写笔记便捷性的应用程序，
it's an app called good notes
叫做 Good Notes。
essentially it makes my idea capturing
它能帮助我在
process before the conversation happens
对话开始前整理思路，还能让
organized but also it allows me to
我
down notes in real time on anything
实时注释研究文档，并记录
that's happening in the conversation but
对话中的任何内容。但
the part I value the most is that all my
我最看重的是，
notes as I'm taking them are synced up
我做的所有笔记都会同步到
with my producer Jack's computer who
我的制作人 Jack 的电脑上，他
sits in the corner of the room which
坐在房间的角落里，这样
keeps this open dialogue between me and
我和他之间就能实时保持对话。
him in real time if you'd like to
如果你想了解更多，可以去
explore goodnotes head to good ./ doac
看看。 前往 Goodnotes.docomo，立即
and start your extended 30-day free
开始您的 30 天免费
trial today or sign up for a yearly
试用，或注册
subscription of just $9.99 head to
仅需 9.99 美元的年度订阅。前往
goodnotes
Goodnotes.docomo。
docomo so what's the debasement of
那么，货币贬值究竟是什么？
currency really simply we talked about
简单来说，我们之前讨论过，
in a digital
在数字
world everything goes to zero in
世界里，一切事物的
value that is De
价值都会归零，这就是所谓的“贬值”。这
basement what it means is too much of
意味着某种东西太多反而会
something makes it less valuable
降低它的价值。
I can come out of the
我可以从沙漠里走出来，
desert I will pay you anything for a
我会花任何价钱买一瓶
water give me a million bottles of water
水；但如果你给我一百万瓶水，
I'll pay you nothing for
我一分钱都不会付。对吧？
them right there's too much of it now
现在东西太多了。
how you say well how can there be too
你可能会问，怎么会有太多的
money but what happens is the economic
钱呢？但实际情况是，
system revalues things in this weird
在这个奇特的
world in this weird
世界里，经济系统会以一种奇特的
way by debasement so debasement in the
方式——贬值——重新评估事物的价值。在
old times was if we take one of
古代，贬值就是一个例子：假设我们拿一枚
those gold coins the basement was that
金币，它的底价是
was let's say 1 o of gold then I was the
1 盎司（约 1.5 盎司）。如果我是
Roman Emperor I would just snip off a
罗马皇帝，我会剪掉一
little bit of the gold you wouldn't
小块金币，你不会
notice and you'd still value it try and
注意到，你仍然会认为它值
pretend it was the 1 oce but somebody
1 盎司。但
else would say no no it's actually worth
其他人会说，不，不。 实际上它的价值
less I've taken that slither as the
更低了。我把那点钱当成
emperor and I've used it and spent it on
皇帝，用它买了
sports cars and you've now got a less
跑车，现在你手里的
coin and the country has less value so
硬币价值降低了，国家的价值也降低了。所以，
the money is less valuable it's called
钱的价值降低了，这叫做“贬值”。
in an electronic age where you just
在电子时代，只要
press the button and you create
按个按钮就能造
money then what happens is the value of
钱，
money goes down so let's say people can
货币贬值就会导致货币贬值。为了让人们更容易
understand it simply as let's say you go
理解，假设你去
on holiday and you go to
度假，去
a country that has a a very weak
一个货币非常疲软的国家，比如说
Mexico let's say you're an American you
墨西哥。假设你是一个美国人，你
went to Mexico everything was cheap
去墨西哥，那里的东西都很便宜，
because the currency kept going down but
因为货币一直在贬值。但
for Mexicans it actually got expensive
对墨西哥人来说，东西却变得很贵，
because the value the purchasing power
因为
your um peso went down and you couldn't
比索的购买力下降了，你
buy as much with your
用比索买不到那么多东西了。
peso what we're doing is ever since
我们现在的情况是，自
2008 the whole world world all the big
2008年以来，全世界所有的大型
economies in the
经济体，
world Hit 100% all the governments hit
所有政府的
100% of GDP in debt so 100% of the
债务都达到了GDP的100%，也就是100%的
economic value of that country was in
经济负担。 那个国家的价值在于其
debt and that means that just paying the
债务，这意味着仅仅支付
interest on that debt starts to become a
债务利息就开始成为一种
burden so let's say your your economy is
负担。假设你的经济
growing at 2% a year let's say your
每年增长2%，
interest rate was
利率也是
2% well 100% of the economic growth
2%，那么经济增长的100%
basically goes to pay the interest
基本上都用来支付利息了，
payments because somebody needs to
因为总得有人来
generate the money to pay them
创造资金来偿还债务。
but at the time corporations were over
但当时，企业和家庭的
100% of GDP in debt and so were
债务都超过了GDP的100%。
households 2008 everybody was in a debt
2008年，每个人都负债累累，
ory the financial system was just
金融体系一直在向
everybody and then it all fell
所有人放贷，然后一切都崩溃了。
apart and so what they stopped doing was
所以，他们停止了
really corporations and households stop
企业和家庭的
um borrowing as much money they in fact
借贷，实际上，他们
restricted money to us so in these
限制了资金流向。因此，在当前的
Economic Times we've actually been able
经济形势下，我们实际上能够
to borrow less money while house prices
借到的钱更少了，而房价却因为货币贬值而
have gone up by debasement I'll show you
上涨。我稍后会解释这
sec and the governments have taken on
一点。政府承担了
this obligation so they've been
这项义务，所以
massively growing their
他们的债务一直在大幅增长。他们
paying debts back in 2008 and only
在2008年将利率重置为零，以期有机会偿还债务。直到
recently have they have they really
最近，利率才真正开始
risen but they've still got all of these
上升。
interest payments to pay for now the US
现在美国经济仍然需要支付大量的利息，
4 well 380 per of GDP in debt I mean
债务占GDP的4380%，
staggering considering the size of this
考虑到美国经济的规模，这简直令人震惊。
economy the world the entire world is
全世界的
400% of GDP and debt but we've gone so
债务总额是GDP的400%，但我们已经
far
远远超出了
beyond what is sensible anymore that
理智的范畴，经济
it's become incredibly fragile so the
变得极其脆弱。因此，
management of the payments of the debt
债务的偿还
and the debt
和债务
itself is the number one Focus Fus of
本身的管理是
the government and the central
政府和
banks because if it all goes to [__] it
央行的首要任务，因为如果一切都崩溃了，
all goes to [__] everyone's going to
每个人都会
lose their savings every business goes
失去积蓄，所有企业都会倒闭，所有
under every government goes under
政府都会垮台，公共服务将
there's no payment of services the
无法支付，
retirees lose everything it is
退休人员将失去一切，这简直
unfathomable and I know many people
难以想象。我知道网上很多人
online talk about yeah we should just
说，我们应该
let it all go they have no comprehension
放任不管，他们根本不理解在
of what that will do in a world that's
一个
400% in debt it's basically a 75%
债务占GDP 400%的世界里，这样做会造成怎样的后果。这基本上意味着所有资产、银行存款、
asset and all the braries and all your
所有
savings and all your pensions and
积蓄、所有养老金
everything so the answer is well let's
等等都将损失75%。所以，他们的答案是，那就
just print some more money to pay the
印更多的钱来支付
bills that's you taking a credit card to
账单吧。
payments now when you control the money
现在，当你掌控资金时，
you can kind of do that because nobody's
你可以用信用卡偿还信用卡欠款，因为没人会
going to tap you on the
来催你。
shoulder so what they do is they start
所以，他们
printing money first they used to used
首先开始印钞。过去，他们使用资产
the the balance sheet which meant that
负债表，这意味着
the Federal Reserve or the bank of
美联储、
England or whoever would buy bonds from
英格兰银行或其他机构会从市场上购买债券，
the market and kind of basically take
基本上将
them off the market so it meant there
它们从市场上撤下，从而
was less debt around in the market but
减少市场上的债务。但
they've changed the thing they they now
他们改变了做法，现在他们
have something more pentious called
使用了一种更隐蔽的东西，叫做
liquidity you can't see it they got
流动性。你看不见它，他们有
different mechanisms that they put this
不同的机制将流动性注入
system and basically everybody all of
系统。基本上，所有
the central banks are doing it at the
中央银行都在
same time and they're also all in
同时这样做，而且他们都
agreement that they have to do it and
同意必须这样做。
this is is all driven by the Aging
这一切都是由人口老龄化
demographics and the debt problems that
及其引发的债务问题驱动的。
caused and so what we've got is every
因此，我们看到的是，每个
government having every four years or so
政府大约每四年就要
to print a lot of money why four years
印一次钞。为什么是四年？
because in 2008 they all reset their
因为在2008年，他们都将
interest rates to zero they then went
利率重置为零，然后
and borrowed money three to five years
借入了三到五年的资金。
out and every four years the
每四年，这个
cycle comes up and they start injecting
周期就会再次出现，他们开始注入
money liquidity Okay so what does this
资金流动性。 这
all mean you know people watching this
一切意味着什么？你知道，正在观看的人可能会说，
like yeah I kind of know what you're
嗯，我大概明白你在
talking about what it means is that on
说什么。这意味着，
average your money goes down in
平均而言，你的钱相
purchasing power versus scarce
对于稀缺
assets by 8% a year and then you've
资产的购买力每年下降8%。然后，
usually got let's say a 3% inflation
假设通货膨胀率为3%，那么
rate you've got 11% of your money is
你的钱每年就会贬值11%。
being devalued every year your future
未来的你会因此变得
self is getting poorer by
贫穷
11% right remember we we talked about
11%，对吧？记住，我们之前讨论过
the future self and if you buy the S&amp;P
未来的自己。如果你购买标普
500 what was it making about 11% a year
500指数，它的年收益率约为11%。
so if you buy the S&amp;P 500 your future
所以，如果你购买标普500指数，未来的你并
self is not going to get any richer for
不会因为
the risk you've taken locking up your
你把
money for 10 years or 20 years because
钱锁定10年或20年而变得更富有，因为通货膨胀和货币贬值。
debasement debasement now people confuse
现在人们常常把
inflation and
通货膨胀和
debasement I would call this debasement
货币贬值混淆，我会把这种情况称为
of currency and so this is happening 8%
货币贬值。这种情况每年发生8%，这
a year which is why we're all feeling so
就是为什么我们都感觉如此
[__] it's happening all these assets
糟糕。所有这些资产都在不断
keep going going up real estate keeps
上涨，房地产价格也在不断上涨，试图
going up to offset this now what I did
抵消这种贬值的影响。我曾经做过一件事。
once I realized this something I call
我意识到，我称之为“
the everything code it's a big thesis
万物密码”的东西，是一个
around how this all happened and what it
围绕这一切如何发生、
all means and what's happening is
意义何在的宏大理论。
basically the Aging population is
基本上，人口老龄化
driving debt to GDP it's driving the
推高了债务占GDP的比重，也推高了
government debt and then the liquidity
政府债务，而流动性则用于
is paying the interest payment so it's
支付利息。
this economic machine that the world has
世界已经变成了一台经济机器，它
become it's perfectly cyclical it's
完美地循环往复，
perfectly predictable it's not going
完全可预测，在
away until we have this technological
我们讨论过的这场技术革命到来之前，它不会消失。
about and so everybody has to protect
所以每个人都必须保护
themselves so once I found this thing
自己。当我发现这个所谓的“
called the everything code I started
万物密码”后，我开始
thinking okay if this let's say
思考：假设
11% rate the hurdle rate of money that
11%的收益率是
my future self is getting poorer every
我未来
year by what do I invest in so I started
每年财富缩水的门槛，那么我应该投资什么？于是我开始用这个收益率除以所有投资标的。结果发现，
dividing everything by that and the S&amp;P
标普
500 doesn't make you any money real
500指数不赚钱，
estate doesn't really make you any money
房地产也不赚钱，
gold actually lost your money supposed
黄金实际上会让你亏钱，它本应
power I'm like holy [__] there were only
保值。我当时就震惊了，
two Assets in the world that
世界上只有两种资产的
outperformed this technology crypto the
表现优于科技股——加密货币。
NASDAQ was doing 18% a year and crypto
纳斯达克指数的年收益率是18%，而加密货币的年收益率
was doing 150 plus you know salana is
是150%以上。 我知道Salana
250% a year even with three 80% draw
即使经历了三次80%的回撤，每年也能实现250%的收益。正是
Downs so this is what got me to change
这一点促使我彻底改变了
my entire investing game from being a
我的投资策略，从一个
broad-based
广泛
investor with you know a balanced
投资、构建均衡投资组合的投资者，转变为专注于
portfolio to okay there's only two bets
两大
in the world there are literally two
领域：
bets in the world technology and
科技和
crypto and the NASDAQ is down
加密货币。
99.97% versus Bitcoin since 2012 how
自2012年以来，纳斯达克指数相对于比特币下跌了99.97%。
much of your personal money did you
你个人投入了多少资金
invest in crypto 100% of my liquid net
到加密货币？我100%的流动净
worth and it has been five years have
资产都投了进去。五年过去了，
you done well
你做得怎么样？很好，非常好。
yeah yeah very well I've I've not made
我没有犯过
any major mistakes I mean I've been in
任何重大错误。我的意思是，我
this journey since 2013 I I have made
从2013年就开始涉足加密货币领域，当然也犯过一些
mistakes my mistake was I bought it at
错误。我的错误是，我在200美元的时候买入了它。
considering how unproven it was in 2013
考虑到2013年加密货币的未经证实，这笔投资不算少。它
up it went
上涨了，在
months of me buying it I'm like I'm the
我买入后的前三个月里，它上涨了五倍左右。我当时觉得自己是
best investor in the world is amazing
世界上最棒的投资者，真是太棒了。
then it fell 87% and I'm like I had this
然后它就下跌了。 当时我持有87%的比特币，心想
long-term view it was going to 100,000
它最终会涨到10万美元，
and that um I would just not look at the
所以就没太在意
price as you're doing right and fine and
价格，觉得现在的策略是对的，没问题。到了
2017 it was now at 2 a half th000 I was
2017年，它已经涨到了2500美元，我
up like 10 12x which was amazing I'd
赚了10到12倍，这简直太棒了，我以前从来
never had a bet up 10 or 12x and and
没有哪笔投资能赚到10到12倍。当时发生了
there was some weird stuff going on
一些奇怪的事情，好像出现了
there was another Bitcoin it was going
另一个比特币，
to be the code had been forked and I was
代码被分叉了。我当时就想，我
like I don't really understand this I'm
不太明白这是怎么回事，我决定把
going to take my money so that was about
钱取出来。大概是2017年3月到
17 by December it had hit
4月之间，到了12月，它涨到了
20,000 it had gone up another 10x that
2万美元，那一年又涨了10倍。
year then it collapsed down
然后它暴跌了
85% and then I bought it in
85%。
2020 during the pandemic into that big
2020年疫情期间，我又在
sell where it fell 50 % so I bought it
它暴跌50%的时候买入了。我当时买得很
cheap I sold it on the way up I then
便宜，上涨的时候卖掉了，下跌的时候又
bought it when it sold
买了。
off if I'd have just held on to my
如果我当初坚持持有
original bet I'd have made five times as
最初的那笔投资，现在会怎么样呢？ 我本可以赚到五倍的
much money and if I'd have listened to
钱，如果我听从了
myself which is every four years when
自己的建议——每四年一次的
you have these big sell-offs you just
大抛售，你应该
try and add as much money as possible
尽可能多地买入——
I'd have made 25 times as much money so
我本可以赚到25倍的钱。所以，
I've even though I got it right I [__]
即使我做对了，我也搞砸了。
too well youve said that the best trade
你说过，最好的交易
always quality of life yes if your
永远是生活质量。是的，如果你的
account is full of quality of life and
账户里装满了生活质量和
quality of life experiences that's the
生活体验，那就是
greatest trade on Earth and I'll
地球上最棒的交易，我会
continue to do that trade until the day
一直这样做，直到我生命的尽头。
die what do you
你是什么
mean what is the purpose of
意思？人生的意义是什么？
life now we can get very existential
我们现在可以深入探讨一些存在主义的
about stuff and you actually go down
问题，实际上，在
these paths a lot with AI and Universal
人工智能、宇宙意识等等领域，我们经常会遇到这种情况。
but basically
但基本上，
let's just assume we're humans let's
假设我们是人类，
just assume maybe we've got one shot on
假设我们在
this Earth well you might as well make
这个地球上只有一次机会，那么你最好充分利用它。
it and people have got to remember money
人们必须记住，金钱
is just a scoring system that allows you
只是一个评分系统，它赋予你
Privileges and people lose track of that
特权。人们常常忘记这一点，
and think money is the privilege
认为金钱本身就是特权。真正的特权
itself the privilege is freedom the
是自由，
privilege is being able to live where
是能够住在
you want to live the privilege is being
你想住的地方。 享受特权意味着被
surrounded by the people you want to be
你想与之相伴的人围绕，享受
surrounded by the privilege is being a
特权意味着
bring up a family whatever your value
组建家庭，无论你的
system is those are the
价值观是什么，这些都是
things
特权。对
so for me it's I like living in
我来说，我喜欢生活在
nature and that's probably key thing
大自然中，这可能是最重要的第一点，
number one but being
但与自然保持
connected so when I bought a house in
联系也很重要。所以，当我在
Spain like that was a huge quality of
西班牙买房时，生活质量得到了极大的提升，
life thing because I've got a security
因为我拥有了一处安全的
of a house that I
房子，置身于
in nature in good climate okay I'm I'm
大自然中，气候宜人。好吧，我
fine but really experiences are even
很好。但实际上，体验更加
more powerful if there is a true
强大。如果说
currency in the world it's experiences
世界上有什么真正的货币，那就是体验。
you know as I said I've just come back
你知道，就像我说的，我刚从赞比亚
from living in the remote world of
的偏远地区回来，那
Zambia that is an experience that is
是一段
incredibly valuable to me and I've done
对我来说无比珍贵的经历。我经历过
a lot of these that is what it's all for
很多这样的事情，这一切都是为了
this understanding and seeing of how the
理解和见识
world is and the beauty and the Marvel
世界的本来面目，欣赏它的美丽和奇妙，
the people understanding people and not
理解人与人之间的差异，不
being fearful of people and and not
害怕人，不以“
of oh well that's their culture and
哦，那是他们的文化，
that's their culture as opposed to
那是他们的文化”这种眼光看待文化，而是要区分
culture good culture
文化的好坏。
bad friends you know all of these things
所有这些
these are the valuable things you can't
才是真正宝贵的东西，你
buy any of them you have to physically
买不到。 你必须亲自
go and spend the time and be
去体验，花时间，忍受
uncomfortable I've always said there is
不适。我一直说，
your comfort zone and where the magic
舒适区和奇迹发生的地方是相通的，
and these two ven diagrams don't
而这两个维恩图并不
intersect you have to be outside your
相交。你必须走出
comfort zone to feel the magic if not
舒适区才能感受到奇迹，否则
you're just doing Life by Numbers do I
你只是在按部就班地生活。我
need money to have those experiences no
需要钱才能拥有这些体验吗？不需要。那
so so what's the point in me doing all
我做这一切的意义何在？
this you know Bitcoin
你知道，投资比特币，
investing focusing and sacrificing my
专注于此，牺牲我的
20s you need some money you don't you
二十几岁？你需要钱，但你不需要。你可以不用钱也
can solve for it without but it's hard
能实现，但
if you're living in
如果你住在
Ohio or Birmingham or wherever you are
俄亥俄州、伯明翰或其他任何地方，那就很难了。对吧？想要
right to get some of these things it
拥有这些东西，
might be I want to be warm and dry I
可能是我想要温暖干燥的环境，可能是我
want to you know grow my own fruit and
想要自己种植水果蔬菜，
veget whatever it is doesn't matter
无论是什么，都无关紧要。
right you can solve it by a number of
你可以用很多
different ways but really for the
不同的方法来实现，但对
average person I say this is like if you
普通人来说，这就好比你
want to live on a beach you can either
想住在海滩边，你可以
become a billionaire and live in some
成为亿万富翁，住在豪华
Barts or you can go to Latin America and
酒店里，或者你可以去拉丁美洲，
live on the be for virtually nothing and
几乎不用花钱就能住在海滩边。
if you're living in an inent age you can
如果你生活在一个新兴时代，你可以
make it happen but then what happens is
实现它，但…… 事情的经过
maybe you want some more Creature
可能是，你想要更多物质
Comforts maybe you do this look I don't
享受，也许你会这样想。我并不是
say that we should all be the Buddhist
说我们都应该像佛教
zen master and say we need nothing we
禅师那样，什么都不需要，
can reject
可以拒绝
everything but if we break it down to
一切。但如果我们把问题分解成“
what is the feeling that I want then you
我想要的感觉是什么”，那么
can solve it with money or without money
无论有没有钱，你都可以解决它，
and you won't be disappointed because
而且你不会失望。因为
remember the very beginning of our
记住，我们
conversation is what makes people
谈话的开头就提到，人们
unhappy is when their vision of their
不快乐的原因在于他们对
future self and their current state
未来的憧憬和现状
don't
不符。
meet now if your vision of your future
如果你对未来的憧憬是，记得
self is remember I said I want that that
我说过，我想要
peninsula in Spain where that family so
西班牙的那个半岛，想要那个家庭，那么
what are the component parts that I like
我喜欢的组成部分是什么呢？
C I like uh social life of people uh I
我喜欢……人们的社交生活……我
like natural beauty and with somebody I
喜欢自然美景，还有我
love okay that can be solved hundred
爱的人。好吧，这可以用一百种
different ways but in your life did you
不同的方法解决。但在你的人生中，你是否经历
have to shift from from the building
过从“建设
Zone the building season of life to then
期”——人生的积累阶段——过渡到“
the kind of enjoyment season of life I
享受期”？我是在人生的
middle which was the lesson I learned is
中间阶段完成的，这也是我学到的教训。
I had done the investment banking in the
我曾经在
hedge fund thing I then opted out the
对冲基金从事投资银行工作，后来我退出了
rat race I wasn't the richest guy in the
激烈的竞争。我不是世界上最富有的人，
world but I thought you know what if I
但我当时想，你知道吗，如果我
can get a source of income I can live
可以…… 我需要一份收入来源来维持生计，这样
and I can grow my olives and Armond and
我才能种植橄榄和阿蒙德。
I lived in a beautiful house on the side
我住在西班牙
of a national park near a beach town in
一个海滨小镇附近国家公园旁的一栋漂亮的房子里。
Spain I've won the lottery
我中了彩票，
and I started Global macro investor that
创办了全球宏观投资者公司，
ended up becoming a um a much bigger
后来发展壮大，规模更大，
thing because the financial crisis and
因为我预测到了金融危机，而且
predicted it and got all that stuff
预测得非常准确。后来我
so what I found is I'd
发现，我
semi-retired and I was surrounded by
半退休了，身边的
people who weren't really stimulating
人在
intellectually stimulating I made some
智力上缺乏启发性。我交了一些
great friends but he wouldn't have a
很棒的朋友，但他们不会和我进行这样的
conversation like
对话，
this and so I felt
所以我感到很
isolated and then then you know you live
孤独。你知道，
on adrenaline if you're an entrepreneur
如果你是企业家
or you're in financial markets and so
或者在金融市场工作，你就会靠肾上腺素活着，所以
you end up going out to bars and
你最终会去酒吧和
Nightclub you know and I'm like I looked
夜总会。我审视了一下，
at it and I've been there 10 years I'm
我已经在那里待了10年了，我
like I got to get out of this because
想我必须离开这里，因为
I'm excited by life I'm excited I want
我对生活充满热情，我想做
to do the entrepreneur thing I love
企业家，我热爱
investing I just want to be around
投资，我只是想和那些也
people who also did it and but by chance
做过这件事的人在一起。但机缘巧合之下，
I ended up building a house in the
我最终在……建了一栋房子。 开
Cayman Islands um because it was one of
曼群岛，嗯，因为那是
my dreams I wanted a trop a house on
我梦想之一，我想要一栋
tropical beach I love diving all of this
热带海滩上的房子，我喜欢潜水
stuff and that was the signal to me to
等等，这给了我一个信号，让我决定“管他呢，
go [__] it I'm moving to cman I started
我要搬到开曼群岛”。我创立了
real vision and I started the
Real Vision，开启了我的
entrepreneurs journey and now I've got
创业之旅，现在我拥有
four companies and I'm busier than I've
四家公司，比我
ever been in my life I'm very happy
人生中任何时候都忙。我非常享受现在的生活，
doing it but it's a chapter again and
但这又是人生的一个新篇章，
it'll give me the life style ratchet but
它不仅能提升我的生活方式，还能提升我的
also the intellectual ratchet that I
智力，我
wanted to prove to myself that I can do
想借此证明自己可以做到
some of these things we have a closing
这些。我们这个
tradition on this podcast where the last
播客有个结尾的传统，上一位
guest leaves a question for the next
嘉宾会给下一位嘉宾留下一个问题，而下一位
guest not knowing who they're going to
嘉宾并不知道问题会留给谁。
for I've never revealed the last
我从未透露过最后一个
question in terms of who's written it
问题是谁写的，
but I'm going to reveal it in this case
但这次我要揭晓答案。
this question is written by Boris
这个问题是鲍里斯·
Johnson and the question was have you
约翰逊写的，问题是：你有没有
ever tried to sack someone and ended the
试图解雇某人，结果却
meeting having accidentally promoted
意外地提拔了
them Boris is speaking from experience
他？鲍里斯以亲身经历回答这个问题。
there you know I
你知道，我
think I probably
想我可能有过，我
have I think I probably have and that
想我可能有过。这又
goes back to one of my things that I've
回到了我的一个话题…… 我
had to learn is how to have difficult
不得不学习如何进行棘手的
conversations I'm English and my mom's
对话。我是英国人，我妈妈是
Dutch we're also quite evasive we don't
荷兰人，我们都比较善于回避，不
like drama my wife's American so she's
喜欢戏剧化的场面。我妻子是美国人，她
taught me that like just go straight in
教我直接切入正题，直奔主题。
for the kill and I've avoided tough
我一直都在逃避棘手的
conversations and so I've probably ended
对话，所以可能最终陷入了
up in that
那种
situation or something close to it does
境地，或者类似的境地。
per I have as well of course I have and
当然，我也有过类似的经历。我
I'm just like but it's the lesson I'm
只是想说，但我
trying to learn is you need to be
想学习的教训是，
more if it's a tough conversation just
如果遇到棘手的对话，你需要更加勇敢地面对它。阿门。
amen thank you R um I think everybody
谢谢你，R。嗯，我认为每个人都
should go and check out your channel
应该去看看你的频道，
which I've watched for many many years
我已经关注你很多年了。
now I think it's the in fact it's the
事实上，
only Channel I go looking for when I'm
当我在
looking for advice on anything crypto
寻找任何与加密货币、
related the macro environment inflation
宏观环境、通货膨胀等相关的建议时，它都是我唯一会去
that I trust and that I go looking for
寻找的频道。我唯一信任并会去寻找的频道，
and I really really mean this when I say
我是真心这么认为的，
it has always been yours because I think
因为
you've provided um Nuance in a way
你一直以来都以一种普通人也能轻松理解的方式，提供了细致入微的见解。
Finance channels are very difficult to
频道里那些
like understand the terminology they
术语很难理解，他们
kind of skipped past that part but what
似乎跳过了那部分，但
you've done so well is made all of these
你做得非常出色的一点是，你让所有这些
subjects so accessible for everybody um
主题都变得如此通俗易懂，人人都能理解。
and I can't imagine how many millions of
我无法想象
people you've um helped open their eyes
你帮助了多少人，让他们看清了
to the state of currency debasement and
货币贬值的现状，以及
you know some of the myths around how to
一些关于如何
create and and save your wealth and I
创造和保住财富的迷思。我
think that's um a mission that is so
认为这是一项
incredibly important because a lot of
极其重要的使命，因为
this Insight unfortunately historically
不幸的是，历史上很多这类洞见都只为
has been reserved for the elites however
精英阶层所拥有，无论
you want to Define them the elites
你怎么定义他们——是
intellectually or the those only the
知识精英，还是仅仅指那些在
people that work in finance and I think
金融行业工作的人。我认为
what real Vision has done is blown those
真正的远见卓识打破了这些
doors open and you're you've been a a
壁垒，你一直是
champion for me in my life um and and an
我人生中的支持者和
educator for me in my life so that's why
导师，所以
I was very excited to speak to you today
我今天非常高兴能和你对话。
so thank you for what you talk
感谢你的分享，非常感谢。
appreciate that and also for everybody
也感谢所有
watching this look I'm genuine in trying
观看这段视频的人，我真心想
to help as many people and so we've that
帮助尽可能多的人，所以我们才有了“万物
the this whole everything code thesis to
皆可编码”这个理论，为了
make people understand it more we've
让人们更好地理解它，我们
made a whole special uh error for you
制作了…… 给你们准备了一份特别的……呃……错误报告，
guys in real verion go to real
在 RealVerion 网站上，请访问 realversion.com 的“
diary and there is all for for you guys
日记”页面，那里有所有为你们准备的内容，包括
this it's the everything code the
所有代码和
document so you can read it watch the
文档，所以你们可以阅读文档并观看
video you get free real verion
视频。你们可以免费
subscription because it's free to
订阅 RealVerion，因为它是免费的。说
join and honestly there's so many tools
实话，那里有很多工具。
and if you don't understand something
如果有什么不明白的地方，可以
ask the AI the bottom right of the
问问屏幕右下角的 AI，
screen there's a little button you ask
那里有个小按钮，你可以问问
the AI the real Vision bot it'll explain
RealVision 机器人，它会为
it to you everything you need is there
你解释。你需要的一切都在那里，而且
it's free there's no reason not to
是免费的。没有理由不
unfuck your own future I'll link that
拯救你的未来。我会在
below so everyone's got it that's
下面放上链接，这样每个人都能找到。这就是
realvision tocom diary there'll be a
RealVision 的“日记”页面，
link below in the description wherever
链接会在下面的描述中。无论
you're listening to this um thank you
你在哪里收听，都会有链接。嗯，谢谢，
thank you I really enjoyed it thank for
谢谢，我真的很喜欢，感谢
your
你们
time every single time you eat you have
每次抽出时间。 饮食是你
an opportunity to improve your health
改善健康的机会，
that's why I love Zoe because it helps
这就是我喜欢 Zoe 的原因，因为它能帮助
me to make the smartest food choices for
我做出最明智的饮食选择。
my body as you guys probably know Zoe is
你们可能知道，Zoe 是
a sponsor of my podcast I'm also an
我的播客赞助商，我也是这家
investor in the company which is
公司的投资者。
important to say I invested in the
我投资这家
company because Zoe combines My Health
公司很重要，因为 Zoe 将我的健康
Data with their worldclass science using
数据与他们世界一流的科学相结合。通过
these two things Zoe guides me to Better
这两方面，Zoe 每次都能指导我
Health every single time I make a food
做出更健康的饮食
choice and eat which means I have more
选择，这意味着我
energy better sleep better mood and I'm
精力更充沛、睡眠更好、心情更愉悦，而且不那么容易感到
less hungry and the best part about Zoe
饥饿。Zoe 最棒的地方在于
is that it's backed by their recent
它得到了他们最近一项
clinical trial something called the
名为“
method study which is the gold standard
方法研究”（Method Study）的临床试验的支持，这是
of scientific research I started Zoe
科学研究的黄金标准。我一年多前开始使用 Zoe，
able to track my progress week after
每周都能追踪自己的进展，
week so I can learn how to be even
从而学习如何在下
smarter the week after and if you
一周做得更好。如果你
haven't joined Zoe yet I'm going to give
还没有加入 Zoe，
you 10% off when you join Zoe today just
今天加入 Zoe 即可享受 10% 的折扣，只需
use the code stepen 10 at checkout so
在结账时使用优惠码 stepen10 即可。
many of you have asked me for a bloody
很多人都问我要
code for Zoe and here is your
Zoe 的优惠码，现在
opportunity Steven tenet checkout there
机会来了！Steven tenet 结账
may not be another one
可能不会再有第二个了
[Music]
[音乐]
ah
啊